{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Responses to these documents were penned by Robert Yates, George Clinton, and Mercy Otis Warren. The fifty-first of these documents praises \"the greatest of all reflections of human nature\" in a description of \"checks and balances.\" For 10 points, name these documents which were written by John Jay, James Madison and Alexander Hamilton in favor of the Constitution.",
      "answer": "Federalist Papers"
    },
    {
      "question": "The third generation of this group was bankrupted in 1981 by a lawsuit engineered by Morris Dees. This group originally formed in Pulaski, Tennessee and was targeted by the Force Act, but formed again after a 1915 meeting on Stone Mountain. Nathan Bedford Forrest was the original Grand Wizard of this group, which targeted Republicans and black voters. For ten points, name this white supremacist organization, which dressed in white hoods.",
      "answer": [
        "Ku Klu Klan",
        "KKK",
        "the Klan"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "IBM introduced the first consumer model of this device in 1975 under the name \"3800.\" In the 1980s, Apple manufactured a popular line of these devices in the Writer series. These devices were invented by Gary Starkweather, who came up with the idea of using an \"image drum.\" For 10 points, name these high-speed, toner-consuming devices for paper output.",
      "answer": "laser printers"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man, who had a vision of dew falling on grass during a solar eclipse, was interviewed by Thomas Gray after his capture. This man killed the Travis family before his capture at Jerusalem, and he is fictionalized in a William Styron book about his \"confessions.\" For 10 points, name this leader of an 1831 slave rebellion in southeastern Virginia.",
      "answer": "Nat Turner"
    },
    {
      "question": "Many participants in this event came from Mary Ann M'Clintock's Yearly Meeting movement, which sought to reform decision-making among Quakers. Frederick Douglass spoke at this event, which adopted the Declaration of Sentiments. For 10 points, name this 1848 convention at which Lucretia Mott and Elizabeth Cady Stanton began the women's rights movement.",
      "answer": "Seneca Falls Convention"
    },
    {
      "question": "Henning von Tresckow modified a plan for running the government if this event ever happened. Claus von Stauffenberg attempted to perform this action when he left a briefcase bomb under the target's desk in the Wolf Lair. For 10 points, name this never realized action that would have removed the head of the Third Reich.",
      "answer": "assassination of Adolf Hitler"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man replaced Robert M. La Follette, Jr. in the Senate after a primary campaign in which he accused La Follette of war profiteering. This man was the subject of the \"Declaration of Conscience Speech\" and Joseph Welch's remark that he had \"no sense of decency.\" For 10 points, name this Wisconsin Senator who worked with Roy Cohn to find Communists.",
      "answer": "Joseph McCarthy"
    },
    {
      "question": "The first four holders of this title were called \"rightly-guided\", or rashidun. Two claimants to this title fought at Karbala. A research center called the House of Wisdom was built under a holder of this title named Harun al-Rashid, who ruled from Baghdad. For 10 points, name this Islamic title used by the Umayyads and Abbasids, which means \"successor to the Prophet.\"",
      "answer": "caliphs"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's memoir noted that the FBI sent agents to take notes on his bar mitzvah in an attempt to prove his parents' Communist Party membership, which he admitted. This man wrote His Holiness, a biography of Pope John Paul II, and the Hillary Clinton bio A Woman in Charge. For 10 points, name this reporter who broke the Watergate story with Bob Woodward.",
      "answer": "Carl Bernstein"
    },
    {
      "question": "A prominent player of this instrument was surreptitiously recorded on the obscene \"Bus\nTapes.\" Jo Jones played this instrument in the Count Basie Orchestra, and it was played by the\nleader of the Jazz Messengers, Art Blakey. For 10 points, name this jazz instrument played by\nJoe Morello of the Dave Brubeck Quartet, Max Roach and Buddy Rich, who used sticks while\nplaying.",
      "answer": [
        "drums"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This route's eastern half was used by people who split off onto the Mormon or Bozeman paths\ninstead of finishing this route. This route existed for twenty-five years before it became suitable\nfor wagon usage as far as Fort Hall. At the end of its use, it went all the way to the Willamette\nValley. For 10 points, name this iconic route used by settlers to the Pacific Northwest.",
      "answer": "Oregon Trail"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man forced Gustavo Leigh out of his government for demanding a date for transition to\ndemocracy. This man came to power after his predecessor nationalized the copper industry, and\nwhile in power he relied on a group of economic advisors called the Chicago Boys. For 10\npoints, name this dictator who overthrew Salvador Allende to take control of Chile.",
      "answer": [
        "Augusto Pinochet",
        "Pinochet",
        "Augusto Jose Ramon Pinochet Ugarte"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man once walked all the way across Virginia lengthwise to secure a promised spot in\ncollege at Hampton. He promised to keep \"as separate as the five fingers on each hand\" and\nadvocated that his followers \"cast down your bucket where you are.\" For 10 points, name this\nman whose Atlanta Compromise speech staked out a moderate civil rights position in 1895.",
      "answer": [
        "Booker T. Washington",
        "Washington"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Early objects created using this device are called incunabula. This device was introduced to\nVenice by Aldus Manutius and brought to England by William Caxton. A goldsmith from Mainz\nused a screw-press for his \"movable-type\" version of this device. For 10 points, name this device\nfirst created in the West by Johannes Gutenberg.",
      "answer": "printing press"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1861, Johann Reis arguably accomplished this task by making use of magneto-restriction.\nElisha Gray claimed to have accomplished this task, though he lost out on a patent to the man\nwho is generally credited with this accomplishment and used the result to transmit, \"Watson,\ncome here, I want you.\" For 10 points, name this achievement of Alexander Graham Bell.",
      "answer": [
        "inventing the telephone",
        "telephone"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A poem which became a protest song about this activity compares the \"scent of magnolias,\nsweet and fresh\" to the \"sudden smell of burning flesh.\" Federal attempts to crack down on this\npractice included the Dyer Bill. Ida B. Wells was an activist against this practice, which is the\nsubject of \"Strange Fruit.\" For 10 points, identify this practice of extrajudicial mob killings of\nblacks.",
      "answer": [
        "lynchings"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During World War II, this character's comic strip recruited children into metal recycling crews known as the Junior Commandos. This character was named after a James Whitcomb Riley poem by her creator, cartoonist Harold Gray. For 10 points, name this character who, in a musical adaptation, sings about her \"Hard Knock Life\" and \"Tomorrow.\"",
      "answer": "Little Orphan Annie"
    },
    {
      "question": "Joseph Haydn composed pieces in this genre named for \"a time of war\" and Horatio Nelson. Leoš Janáček (lay-OHSH yuh-NAH-chek) used a dead Slavonic language to create the \"Glagolitic\" example of this form, which was used for a piece in B minor by J.S. Bach. For 10 points, name this genre which sets the \"Kyrie\" (KEER-ee-ay), \"Credo,\" and other parts of a liturgy.",
      "answer": "mass"
    },
    {
      "question": "Members of this group built Bodrum Castle, partly from the ruins of the Mausoleum of Halicarnassus. This organization lost Malta after refusing to let Napoleon’s fleet enter its port. Earlier, they lost the island of Rhodes to Suleiman the Magnificent after a 1522 siege. For 10 points, name this crusading order named for their original mandate of caring for the sick.",
      "answer": "Knights Hospitaller"
    },
    {
      "question": "A major doctrinal influence on this group was Joseph Franklin Rutherford, who reformed the Bible Student associations and promoted its belief that Jesus was crucified on a tree rather than a cross. This group, which traces its founding to Charles Taze Russell, published The Watchtower. For 10 points, name this sect known for proselytizing and not accepting blood donations.",
      "answer": "Jehovah's Witnesses"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a painting of this man by Paolo Veronese, the old woman Sisygambis confusedly addresses this man’s close friend Hephaestion while begging for mercy. In a depiction of this ruler, a giant scroll in Latin describing the casualties of the battle flies over the two armies fighting. For 10 points, name this Macedonian king who was depicted fighting Darius III in The Battle of Issus.",
      "answer": "Alexander the Great"
    },
    {
      "question": "These people, who acquired a cult following after the discovery of the \"Joplin photos,\" worked with Ralph Fults and Henry Methvin prior to their death in Bienville, Louisiana. A landmark 1967 film about these people starred Faye Dunaway and Warren Beatty. For 10 points, identify this 1930s criminal pair who were killed in a shootout with police.",
      "answer": "Bonnie Parker and Clyde Barrow"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man started his career in organized crime as an associate of Tony Accardo, who controlled several corrupt sherrifs in Texas. This man made a strange remark to Seth Kantor at Parkland Hospital; later, he went to the Dallas police headquarters and claimed he was trying to \"spare Jackie from testifying.\" For 10 points, name this man who killed Lee Harvey Oswald.",
      "answer": "Jack Ruby"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man focused on social productive forces, his nation’s advanced culture, and the interests of the majority as his “Three Represents” doctrine. This man succeeded Zhao Ziyang as General Secretary after the former’s dismissal by Deng Xiaoping after the Tiananmen Massacre. For 10 points, name this leader of the Chinese Communist Party during the 1990s.",
      "answer": "Jiang Zemin"
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization was led in the mid-twentieth century by Walter White, who oversaw publication of its journal, The Crisis. This organization was founded out of the Niagara Movement following the 1908 Springfield riot by people such as W.E.B. Du Bois. For 10 points, name this black civil rights group, which successfully argued the Brown v. Board case.",
      "answer": "NAACP"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Sassanian king Khosrau II owned a napkin made of this material which he cleaned in a startling way in front of guests. Quebec's Thetford Hills were a major mining site for this material, which forms fibers approximately of the same size and shape of chromosomes. For 10 points, name this material once used for fireproofing, now known to cause mesothelioma.",
      "answer": "asbestos"
    },
    {
      "question": "These things made use of a part known as the Canadarm to manipulate outside objects. In the late 1970s, a partially-functional model of this kind of object, the Enterprise, was built. The Endeavour was the last created of these things; two of them, including the Columbia, were destroyed in accidents. For 10 points, name this kind of vessel that includes the Challenger.",
      "answer": "space shuttle"
    },
    {
      "question": "A failed action at this place was funded by the \"Secret Six\" and ended by then-U.S. army officer Robert E. Lee. This place was targeted because its placement at a junction of the B&O Railroad had made it an ideal storage site for army supplies, which were to be stolen for an insurrection. For 10 points, name this town, now in West Virginia, where John Brown launched a failed raid.",
      "answer": "Harpers Ferry"
    },
    {
      "question": "The election of Stephen Langton to one post led to the signing of this document, which was supported by the Charter of the Forest. One clause from this document formed a council of 25 nobles to ensure its enforcement while another dealt with the removal of fish weirs. This document was proposed after a ruler lost the Battle of Bouvines and signed at Runnymede. For ten points, name this 1215 document signed by King John of England which granted rights to barons.",
      "answer": "Magna Carta"
    },
    {
      "question": "Potential violations of this law are considered using the “rule of reason” doctrine. The Danbury Hatters court case applied this law to labor unions, but it did not apply to manufacturing after the government failed in their suit against the E.C. Knight Company. The Standard Oil Company was broken up using, for ten points, what 1890 antitrust law, named for an Ohio senator and later modified by the Clayton Antitrust Act?",
      "answer": "Sherman Antitrust Act"
    },
    {
      "question": "PETA has protested a ritual held one day before this holiday in which a chicken is swung over the head, then donated to charity. The Ne´ılah is read on this day, the tenth of Tishrei, which includes five prayer services and fasting. In 1973, this holiday was marred by a surprise attack in the Sinai Peninsula by Egypt against Israel. For ten points, name this Jewish Day of Atonement, the holiest day of the Jewish year.",
      "answer": "Yom Kippur or Day of Atonement before mention"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man created a system of “burhs” for the defense of his kingdom, which eventually became known as “boroughs”. This man’s forces were attacked at Chippenham, which saw him retreat to Athelney. This man’s life was chronicled by Bishop Asser, and he converted the Danish king Guthrum to Christianity. For ten points, name this Anglo-Saxon king of Wessex in the 800s AD, the only English king to be given the epithet “the Great”.",
      "answer": "Alfred the Great or Alfred I"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Maori base their new year on the appearance of one star cluster in this constellation, to which the Parthenon is also oriented. In 1054, the first object cataloged by Messier appeared in this constellation, whose alpha star was named by Arabic astronomers for its following of the Pleiades. The Crab Nebula and Aldebaran are found in this constellation, which has been identified as Marduk, Nandi, and Io by various myth systems. For ten points, name this constellation, depicted by many ancient civilizations as a bull.",
      "answer": "Taurus"
    },
    {
      "question": "The “imminent lawless action” test was formed after Clarence Brandenburg, a member of this group, sued the state of Ohio. The first leader of this organization was a general whose forces committed the Fort Pillow Massacre. A revival of this group at Stone Mountain took place after it was depicted suppressing voters in D. W. Griffith’s film Birth of a Nation. Nathan Bedford Forrest helped found, for ten points, what white supremacist organization?",
      "answer": "Ku Klux Klan"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Alma-Ata Protocols were signed in the wake of this event, and one man’s proclamation of the “Sinatra Doctrine” encouraged this event. One leader was imprisoned in his dacha at Foros prior to this event, which led to the formation of the CIS. The ascension of Boris Yeltsin marked the end of, for ten points, what event which led to the independence of Ukraine, Belarus, and many other countries?",
      "answer": [
        "Dissolution of the USSR",
        "synonyms for dissolution,",
        "Soviet Union for USSR"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One speech given in this location referenced a John Magee poem, noting that seven people, including Ronald McNair, had “slipped the surly bonds of Earth to touch the face of God.” After a meeting in this location, Elvis Presley was given a badge for the Bureau of Narcotics and Dangerous Drugs. A photograph taken in this location shows a child playing beneath the Resolute Desk, Richard Nixon called the Apollo 11 astronauts from, for ten points, what room located in the West Wing in the White House?",
      "answer": "Oval Office"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Sullivan-Hoey law was passed in response to this incident. This event helped spur the growth of the ILGWU after the “Uprising of 20,000.” This event started on the eighth floor of the Asch building, whose main exits were locked on orders of the owners, Max Blanck and Isaac Harris. 146 mostly-female garment workers died in, for ten points, what 1911 fire that consumed a New York sweatshop?",
      "answer": "Triangle Shirtwaist Factory Fire"
    },
    {
      "question": "Strict adherence to this religion’s teachings caused the death of Elli Perkins by her schizophrenic son. This faith uses the acronym MEST to describe the physical universe, which can be controlled by Operating Thetans who have undergone “auditing” and the use of E-meters. In this religion, the Supreme Galactic Overlord Xenu detonated hydrogen bombs in volcanoes, as described by the science fiction author of Dianetics. For ten points, name this religion, founded by L. Ron Hubbard and practiced by people such as John Travolta and Tom Cruise.",
      "answer": "Church of Scientology"
    },
    {
      "question": "ThisorganizationabsorbedMaktabal-KhidamatafterthedeathofAbdullahAzzaminacarbombing. A pair of attacks in Dar es Salaam and Nairobi on August 7, 1998, was orchestrated by this organization; those attacks on U.S. embassies prompted its leader to be placed on the FBI’s Most Wanted list. Khalid Sheikh Mohammed and Zacarias Moussaoui were members of this group until their arrest for planning and knowledge of another of this group’s attacks. For ten points, name this Islamic terrorist group that perpetrated the September 11th attacks under Osama bin Laden.",
      "answer": "al-Qaeda"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man, who introduced the litmus test for differentiating acids and bases, used Robert Hooke’s air pump to refute contemporary claims that vacuums don’t exist. He coined the modern usage of the term “element” in 1661’s The Sceptical Chemist. For ten points, name this English scientist whose namesake gas law describes how, at constant temperature, the pressure and volume of a gas are inversely related.",
      "answer": "Robert Boyle"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was arrested by Zhang Xueliang in the Xi’an Incident a year after his forces failed to capture an evading enemy on the Long March. This successor of Sun Yatsen was forced to settle at an island nation after losing a war against the Communist Party. For ten points, name this leader of the Kuomintang who escaped to Taiwan after losing the Chinese Civil War to Mao Zedong.",
      "answer": [
        "Chiang Kai-Shek",
        "Jiang Jieshi"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In Florence, this commodity was produced by the Arte de Lana, and the Ciompi [CHOMP-ee] was an uprising of workers with this commodity. Production of this commodity was the cornerstone of the medieval English economy, where it drove the adoption of enclosure and was exported to the Flemish cloth trade. Eventually replaced in some part by Venetian-imported silk, for ten points, name this material, which one can obtain by shearing a sheep.",
      "answer": "wool"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler, who described himself as the “Beloved of the Gods,” protected his power by assassinating his half-brother Susima. This patron of the Great Stupa at Sanchi and son of Bindusara ruled from Magadha. His visions of bloodshed after winning the Kalinga War led him to convert to Buddhism. For ten points, name this grandson of Chandragupta and emperor of the Mauryans.",
      "answer": "Ashoka the Great"
    },
    {
      "question": "This empire defeated Linghu Chao’s rebels in its successful defense of Yongqiu [yong-chu]. Huang Chao’s rebels against this dynasty slaughtered tens of thousands of foreigners in Guangzhou in 878. This dynasty’s power was interrupted by Wu Zetian’s brief Second Zhou Dynasty and by the An Lushan rebellion. Emperor Gaozufounded, forten points, whatChinese dynasty thatpreceded the Song Dynasty?",
      "answer": "Tang dynasty"
    },
    {
      "question": "Charles Michelson, the head of the DNC, coined the term for these settlements in 1931, and a reservoir where Central Park’s Great Lawn would be built was home to one of the most prominent of these locations. One of these locations in Anacostia Flats was cleared out by Douglas MacArthur to remove the Bonus Army from Washington, D.C. in 1932. For ten points, name these shantytowns formed during the Great Depression, which were named for the predecessor to Franklin Roosevelt.",
      "answer": "Hoovervilles"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was the first athlete to run for 2,000 yards in an NFL season in 1973. He had to auction his 1968 Heisman Trophy, earned at USC, to pay the estate of Ronald Goldman as a result of a civil suit in 1997, two years after Alan Dershowitz and Johnnie Cochran defended this man in the “Trial of the Century”. For ten points, name this former Buffalo Bill running back who was acquitted of murdering his ex-wife, Nicole Brown, in 1995.",
      "answer": "Orenthal James “O.J.” Simpson"
    },
    {
      "question": "Folk singer Dave van Ronk was arrested during this event. The Mattachine Society tried to control rioting after this event. Allen Ginsberg said that some protesters during this event had “lost that wounded look”. The death of Judy Garland has been proposed as a starting point for this event. An NYPD raid on a bar triggered, for ten points, what series of riots in Greenwich Village in 1969 that began the modern gay rights movement?",
      "answer": "Stonewall Inn riots or the raid on the Stonewall Inn itself"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event inspired Charles Perrow’s Normal Accidents, and it was analyzed by the Kemeny commission. A hydrogen bubble was vented into the air four days after this incident, which occurred because of a stuck relief valve in Unit 2. Although nobody died because of this accident near Harrisburg, public reaction to it led to the cancellation of over fifty planned reactors. For ten points, name this 1979 incident in which a Pennsylvania nuclear plant went into partial meltdown.",
      "answer": "Three Mile Island incident or accident, etc."
    },
    {
      "question": "This man gave a series of benefit concerts in response to the Great Fire of Hamburg, and his travels withCountessMaried’AgoultinspiredhisYearsofPilgrimage. Heincludedslow“lassan”andfast“friska” sections in a set of nineteen works, the fifteenth which was based on the “Rakoczi March.” Heinrich Heine coined a term to describe the frenzied reception he received in Berlin. For ten points, name this virtuoso Romantic pianist who wrote the Hungarian Rhapsodies and was the subject of a namesake “mania.”",
      "answer": "Franz Liszt or Liszt Ferenc"
    },
    {
      "question": "One ruler of this dynasty beheaded Jafar Yahya, leading to the decline of the Barmakid family. That ruler of this dynasty, Harun Al-Rashid, created the House of Wisdom and gave Charlemagne the elephant Abul-Abbas. This dynasty’s capital, Baghdad, was sacked by the Mongols in 1258. For ten points, name this Islamic caliphate that succeeded the Umayyad dynasty.",
      "answer": "Abbasid Caliphate"
    },
    {
      "question": "Genoese crossbowmen were hacked down by friendly forces while retreating during this battle, and one commander at this battle adopted the motto and crest of the blind King John of Bohemia, who died at this battle. That commander was refused help by his father in this battle, saying “let the boy win his spurs”; those commanders were Edward the Black Prince and Edward III. The dominance of the longbow was confirmed in, for ten points, what first decisive English victory in the Hundred Years War?",
      "answer": "Battle of Crecy"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man suggested that his superior, Sir Thomas Fairfax, give up his strong position to encourage a hasty attack by Prince Rupert at the Battle of Naseby. In 1653, this Roundhead dismissed the Rump Parliament, the small group of MPs who remained after Pride’s Purge in 1648. Charles I was beheaded on orders of, for ten points, what leader of the New Model Army, known as “Old Ironsides,” who served as Lord Protector after the English Civil War?",
      "answer": "Oliver Cromwell"
    },
    {
      "question": "This work notes that the speaker’s surroundings have been “consecrated [...] far above our poor power to add.” This oration was preceded by a two-hour speech by Edward Everett, and it notes that a “government of the people, by the people, and for the people, will not perish from this earth.” Casualties at a Pennsylvania battlefield were honored with, for ten points, what speech by Abraham Lincoln that opens with the phrase “Four score and seven years ago?”",
      "answer": "Gettysburg Address"
    },
    {
      "question": "A captain of this type of ship, John Worden, was partially blinded in combat from a nearby explosion. John Ericsson designed one of these ships whose wreck was discovered off the coast of Cape Hatteras in 1973 and which mostly floated a foot and a half above the waterline. The USS Cumberland was rammed and sunk by this type of ship, two of which fought to a standstill in the Battle of Hampton Roads. For ten points, name this type of armored ship, exemplified by the Monitor and the Virginia.",
      "answer": "ironclads"
    },
    {
      "question": "The TORCH report investigated the health impacts of this event, which caused the deaths of numerous pine trees in the “Red Forest.” An iron sarcophagus was built to mitigate the aftereffects of this event, which triggered a high rate of thyroid cancer among former citizens of Pripyat. This event was discovered after an incidence of radioactive rain in Sweden. For ten points, name this 1986 nuclear disaster at a Ukrainian power plant.",
      "answer": [
        "Chernobyl disaster",
        "any additional information, like “nuclear meltdown at Chernobyl,” etc."
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Bing Nursery School at this university provided subjects for Walter Mischel’s study on delayed gratification using marshmallows. This school’s Encyclopedia of Philosophy is the most extensive of its type online, and its law school produced Supreme Court justices like William Rehnquist and Sandra Day O’Connor. Philip Zimbardo operated a notorious prison experiment at, for ten points, what private West Coast university founded by a namesake railroad tycoon?",
      "answer": "Stanford University"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man ended the Iberian War in modern-day Georgia by signing a treaty of “Eternal Peace” with the Sassanid ruler Khosrau I. This man’s army reconquered Ravenna from the Ostrogoths thanks to the tactics of Belisarius. The Nika Riots forced this leader to dismiss his advisor Tribonian, who had helped this man issue a legal codex. For ten points, name this husband of Theodora, a Byzantine emperor who ordered the construction of the Hagia Sophia.",
      "answer": "Justinian I or Justinian the Great"
    },
    {
      "question": "The losers of this battle were induced into a mass panic known as the Runaway Scrape. During a meeting in this battle, William Travis drew a line in the sand and allowed all who stepped across to leave. Davy Crockett and Jim Bowie were among the 200 defenders of a San Antonio mission who died in this 1836 battle. For ten points, name this victory for the Mexican army, inspiring a Texan call to “remember [this battle].”",
      "answer": "Battle of the Alamo"
    },
    {
      "question": "This figure stands next to Saint Barbara and Saint Sixtus in a Sistine painting by Raphael. When shown with another religious figure on her lap, this figure is known as the “Seat of Wisdom.” Scenes of the Annunciation show the angel Gabriel entering the house of this woman and her husband Joseph. For ten points, name this religious figure, known in Italian art as Madonna, and often shown holding her son, Jesus Christ.",
      "answer": [
        "the Virgin Mary",
        "either",
        "both",
        "Madonna before mentioned,"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A holder of this position was exhumed and tried for perjury in the Cadaver Trial. Byzantine governors of the Exarchate of Ravenna once appointed people to this position. Gregory the Great reformed this position, which was supposedly given authority over Western Europe by the Donation of Constantine. In the Great Schism, the holder of this position was excommunicated by the Orthodox Church. For ten points, name this religious position, the head of the Catholic Church.",
      "answer": "Pope or Bishop of Rome"
    },
    {
      "question": "Participants in this event were later caught during a gun battle at the Holbeche House. This plan was exposed in a letter addressed to Lord Monteagle, and it strove to replace the sitting monarch with Elizabeth of Bohemia. Robert Catesby helped coordinate this plan, which was scheduled for November fifth. For ten points, name this plot that attempted to blow up James I and English Parliament, but was thwarted when Guy Fawkes was caught.",
      "answer": "Gunpowder Plot"
    },
    {
      "question": "In “Human Bondage,” Spinoza’s 64th proposition notes that the knowledge of this concept is inadequate knowledge and that the human mind could not conceive of this concept if the mind possessed adequate ideas. Skeptical theism is a response to a philosophical “problem” of this concept, first originated logically by Epicurus. In Zurvan theology, Angra Mainyu chose to embody this concept. For ten points, name this moral and ethical concept, often represented in Christian theology by demons and contrasted with “good.”",
      "answer": [
        "evil",
        "word forms and reasonable synonyms, like badness",
        "the Problem of Evil",
        "synonyms of destruction after Angra Mainyu is said",
        "sin and equivalents after Christian is said"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This monarch died at Newark Castle during a conflict with Robert Fitzwalter called the First Barons’ War. This king feuded with Pope Innocent III over his appointment of Stephen Langton to the post of Archbishop of Canterbury. This ruler, who was nicknamed “Lackland,” negotiated a legal document with a group of rebellious noblemen at a meadow at Runnymede. For ten points, name this ruler, the only English king of his name, who signed the Magna Carta in 1215.",
      "answer": [
        "John or John Lackland",
        "John I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man became greatly angry when he found his firstborn had slept with his concubine Bilhah. He gradually claimed the majority of his uncle’s flock of sheep and goats and married two of his daughters. This man was born grabbing the heel of his twin brother, a redheaded hunter who was tricked into bequeathing his birthright to his man. For ten points, name this son of Isaac whose descendants formed the tribes of Israel.",
      "answer": [
        "Jacob",
        "Israel until mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Two Penny Act established that ministers be paid two pennies per pound of this commodity, a move which led to Parson’s Cause. William Cunningham was part of a group of Glasgow merchants known as the “lords” of this commodity. The Orinoco variety of this crop dominated Chesapeake Bay, which was known as “this crop’s” coast. John Rolfe introduced this crop to Jamestown. For ten points, name this cash crop, used in the production of cigarettes.",
      "answer": "tobacco"
    },
    {
      "question": "A month-long hearing in 1954 ended with this man losing his security clearance due to claims, by William Borden, of Communist ties. This man chose Norris Bradbury to replace him as Director of a laboratory that he left in 1945. This man pondered a quote from the Baghavad Gita, “Now I am become Death, the destroyer of worlds,” at the successful Trinity test. For ten points, name this head of the Los Alamos lab during World War II’s Manhattan Project.",
      "answer": "Julius Robert Oppenheimer"
    },
    {
      "question": "This figure’s body was found in the Tallahatchie River, weighed down by a heavy fan. Jet published images of this figure’s funeral, at which his mother insisted on an open casket. After an all-white jury acquitted J.W. Milam and Roy Bryant of murdering this figure, they freely admitted their guilt in an interview with Look magazine. For ten points, name this 14-year-old from Chicago who was murdered in Mississippi in 1955.",
      "answer": "Emmett Till"
    },
    {
      "question": "One ruler with name was the subject of the “Royal Question” and was forced to abdicate by Jean Duvieusart’s government. Otto of Wittelsbach became King of Greece when another ruler of this name rejected that position. The Casement Report details atrocities that occurred under another ruler of this name, who used the Force Publique [puh-BLEEK] to enforce rubber quotas for workers in the Congo. For ten points, give this name shared by three Belgian Kings.",
      "answer": [
        "L´eopold",
        "any/all of L´eopold I, II,",
        "III"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Mount Fortress was built to protect members of this religion. Fumi-e were pictures that members of this religion stepped on to prove innocence. Twenty-six members of this religion were executed after their protection was revoked by the Shimazu clan. “Hidden” members of this religion revolted in the Shimabara Rebellion. This religion was banned by sakoku law in Japan. For ten points, name this religion that was spread to Qing China by Jesuit missionaries.",
      "answer": "Roman Catholicism"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these objects includes an unusually gory depiction of Jesus in the center, was thought to have healing powers, and was created for a hospital for lepers in Isenheim. Another one of these artworks includes a panel showing the Adoration of the Mystic Lamb and a triple-crowned Almighty figure; that example was created by the van Eyck brothers. For ten points, name these religious artworks created for the center of churches, including one in Ghent.",
      "answer": [
        "altarpieces",
        "descriptions like “paintings placed behind an altar”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This political faction was opposed by the White League and the Red Shirts, paramilitary groups that supported the Redeemers. This faction passed legislation that created five districts, each ruled by a different general. Anticipating the dismissal of War Secretary Edwin Stanton, this faction passed the Tenure of Office Act. Thaddeus Stevens led, for ten points, what Reconstruction-era political faction that tried to impeach Andrew Johnson?",
      "answer": "Radical Republicans"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event was preceded by a rally at Blue Island, where anything that could be lit on fire was. Richard Olney helped mitigate this event by obtaining an injunction barring labor leaders from joining it. Though Illinois governor John Peter Altgeld declined to intervene in it, Grover Cleveland sent Nelson Miles’ troops to break it up because it was disrupting federal mail. Eugene Debs was arrested for his role in, for ten points, what 1894 worker’s strike targeting a sleeping car manufacturer?",
      "answer": "Pullman strike"
    },
    {
      "question": "Charles Hamilton Houston’s work for this organization included helping to establish its Legal Defense Fund. This organization, which started publishing the magazine The Crisis in 1910, grew out of the Niagara Movement, whose members were forbidden from staying at segregated hotels in New York state. This organization spearheaded legal challenges to Jim Crow laws in the early 20th century. W.E.B. DuBois helped found, for ten points, what civil rights group?",
      "answer": "NAACP or the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this battle, reinforcements sent down the Hagerstown turnpike dissolved almost immediately when commander Joseph Mansfield was shot. After heavy fighting at Miller’s Cornfield, Dunker Church, and the Bloody Lane, the winning commander was criticized for failing to pursue his foes. The Emancipation Proclamation was issued shortly after this battle. George McClellan won at, for ten points, what 1862 battle in Maryland that proved to be the costliest single day in the Civil War?",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Antietam",
        "Battle of Sharpsburg"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Kenneth Bianchi was arrested in 1979 for committing two murders in Washington and 10 murders in this state as the “Hillside Strangler.” In this state, Elizabeth Short was murdered and her corpse severed in two in what became known as the Black Dahlia Murder. The symbol of a circle with a plus sign drawn through it was used by a murderer in this state who sent four ciphers to the police. For ten points, name this state where the Zodiac Killer terrorized San Francisco.",
      "answer": "California"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s Special Field Order Number 15 provided for the confiscation of land along the Atlantic coast to be allotted among freed slaves, which became the basis for the saying “Forty Acres and a Mule.” This commander presented 25,000 bales of cotton to Abraham Lincoln as a Christmas gift when he captured Savannah in December 1864, the culmination of a campaign of total war. For ten points, name this Union general who captured Atlanta to begin his “March to the Sea.”",
      "answer": "William Tecumseh Sherman"
    },
    {
      "question": "Laryngeal examples of these constructs are generally not found within the English language. The dropping of the voiceless glottal fricative type of these constructs took place during the 13th century. The place and manner of articulation are typically both given when categorizing these constructs, which differ from a similar construct in that they require a complete or partial closure of the vocal tract. For ten points, name these linguistic constructs that are often contrasted with vowels.",
      "answer": "consonants"
    },
    {
      "question": "Production ceilings in this industry were upheld in Wickard v. Filburn. Workers in this industry demanded fair railroad rates after organizing as the Grange. The US imported labor for this industry via the Bracero Program. Dolores Huerta coined the slogan “si, se puede,” which was used by a union in this industry led by Cesar Chavez. For ten points, name this industry whose workers migrated to California to escape the Dust Bowl, despite claims that its plowing would lead to rain.",
      "answer": [
        "agriculture",
        "farming and other equivalents"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A type of these items named for Rule 144 must be acquired in unregistered form. Privately held companiesuseIPOstoinitiatethesaleoftheseitems.Preferredtypesoftheseitemsgrantearlierdividends than their common form, which allows for voting rights in decisions. For ten points, name these financial instruments that are sold on namesake exchanges and which represent ownership of a corporation.",
      "answer": [
        "stocks",
        "any additional information, such as preferred stocks"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This location is the setting of a photo of a boy holding a toy hand grenade by Diane Arbus. Over 7,500 vinyl frames were adorned with saffron nylon fabric during a Christo and Jeanne-Claude exhibit at this location known as The Gates. Belvedere Castle and the Strawberry Fields memorial to John Lennon are located in this park, which was outlined in the Greensward Plan by Calvert Vaux [voh] and Frederick Law Olmsted. For ten points, name this large park in Manhattan.",
      "answer": "Central Park"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this battle, Uluc¸ [oo-looch] Ali was able to capture the standard of the Knights Hospitaller. The Genoese admiral Andrea Doria fought in this battle after a defeat at the Battle of Preveza. Six powerful galleasses were provided by Venice to this battle’s winning side, which was commanded by Don John, the brother of the Holy Roman Emperor Philip II. For ten points, name this decisive 1571 naval victory for a Christian alliance, stopping the Ottoman advance into the Mediterranean Sea.",
      "answer": "Battle of Lepanto"
    },
    {
      "question": "Major John Brown’s failure to reinforce this man’s army in time resulted in Guy Carleton’s capture of this man at the Battle of Longue-Pointe. The day before Seth Warner took Fort Crown Point, this man and Benedict Arnold led a successful capture of a fort whose weapons helped end the Siege of Boston. Fort Ticonderoga was captured by, for ten points, what leader of Vermont’s Green Mountain Boys?",
      "answer": "Ethan Allen"
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization partially titles the autobiography of its one-time leading member, George Plunkitt. This group aided the gubernatorial campaign of John Hoffman, one of its leaders known as Grand Sachems. This organization, which declined after the mayoral election of Fiorello La Guardia in 1934, achieved notoriety for its corruption and abuse of the spoils system under Boss Tweed. For ten points, name this New York City political machine.",
      "answer": "Tammany Hall"
    },
    {
      "question": "After this complex was sacked by Chams, it was replaced in function by the nearby Bayon. This complex is the site of a bas-relief showing Vasuki being pulled by 92 asuras and 88 devas in the “Churning of the Sea of Milk.” This complex was built to resemble Mount Meru and dedicated to Vishnu as a Hindu temple by Suryavarman II, but was later transformed into a Buddhist temple. For ten points, name this Khmer temple complex in Cambodia.",
      "answer": "Angkor Wat"
    },
    {
      "question": "Early versions of this device used rotating Nipkow disks. John Logie Baird pioneered the mechanical type of this device, which was improved upon by devices using image dissector tubes. Philo Farnsworth invented the electric version of this device, which contained cathode ray tubes that use superimposed red, green and blue to display color. For ten points, name this device whose early versions featured black and white broadcasts by NBC and CBS.",
      "answer": [
        "television",
        "TV"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This program was criticized for a slow reaction to the Church Rock mill disaster in 1979. This program began after schools on 93rd and 99th Street were harmed by Hooker Company’s poor management of a landfill in Niagara Falls, New York, leading numerous schoolchildren to be poisoned. Love Canal, the Valley of the Drums, and other locations are judged in the Hazard Ranking System by, for ten points, what federal program that empowers the EPA to clean up hazardous waste sites?",
      "answer": "Superfund"
    },
    {
      "question": "Two weeks after a Robert Geiger news story coined a name for this event, Hugh Bennett was made director of a new agency within the Interior Department. This event prompted the Soil Conservation Act, as it was partly caused by cattle overgrazing. Dorothea Lange’s iconic photograph Migrant Mother depicts a family fleeing, for ten points, what event in which “Okies” attempted to move to California to avoid severe drought during the Great Depression?",
      "answer": "Dust Bowl"
    },
    {
      "question": "Members of this religious movement follow a ruleset called the Ordnung. One of the most conservative sects of this religious group, based in Nebraska, is known for its brown clothing. Some young people from this religious group are allowed to disobey norms in an exploratory period called Rumspringa. Lancaster County, Pennsylvania was a migration site for many members of, for ten points, what religious group known for living without the conveniences of modern technology?",
      "answer": "the Amish"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these events that mainly affected Monterey and Santa Cruz Counties in 1989 temporarily cut off coverage of the World Series and began near Loma Prieta Peak. The Mission District burned in a fire that occurred after one of these events that destroyed the original flag used in the Bear Flag Revolt; that event was centered near the Golden Gate. For ten points, name these type of natural disaster that largely destroyed San Francisco in 1906.",
      "answer": "earthquakes"
    },
    {
      "question": "A brand of these products temporarily stopped using green in its packaging during World War II, supposedly to save copper. Leo Burnett designed a mascot for a company that sold these products in an effort to transition away from feminine ad campaigns; that mascot was a cowboy portrayed by several men who later died of COPD and other respiratory diseases. In 1970, the government banned television advertising for, for ten points, what cancer-causing product sold by Lucky Strike and Marlboro?",
      "answer": [
        "cigarettes",
        "answers related to tobacco"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This one-time head of the “Radical Division” organized COINTELPRO to spy on suspected communists, using the program to harass Martin Luther King. Associates of this man included secretary Helen Gandy, who burned his “personal file” after his death, and his deputy Clyde Tolson. The arrests of Machine Gun Kelly and “Public Enemy Number One” John Dillinger were coordinated by a group led by, for ten points, what influential first director of the FBI?",
      "answer": "John Edgar Hoover"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was accused of staging a standardization demonstration by Merritt Smith in order to buy more time to fulfill a government order for 15,000 muskets. This man worked with Honore Blanc and Louis de Tousard to produce widely-used artillery pieces, an early concept of interchangeable parts. His most famous creation revolutionized the Southern economy by allowing for the easy removal of seeds from a certain cash crop. For ten points, name this inventor of the cotton gin.",
      "answer": "Eli Whitney"
    },
    {
      "question": "JME McTaggart formulated two possible conceptions of this concept, the A-series and B-series, in his work on the “Unreality” of this concept. Martin Heidegger’s magnum opus argued that this concept was “the horizon of being” and was titled for Being and this concept. Philosophical positions about this concept include presentism and eternalism. For ten points, name this philosophical concept which pertains to the past, present, and future.",
      "answer": [
        "time",
        "The Unreality of Time",
        "Being and Time"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This group placed former king Norodom Sihanouk under house arrest after a break in their alliance. This group transformed a high school into the notorious torture center S-21. After overthrowing Lon Nol to take power, this group set the calendar to “Year Zero” and sought to create an agrarian society. The “killing fields” were operated by, for ten points, what communist organization led by Pol Pot that ruled Cambodia in the 1970s?",
      "answer": "Khmer Rouge"
    },
    {
      "question": "A cartoon satirizing this meeting shows three men on the edge of a cliff and is partly titled LEAP NO LEAP. Delegates known as “Blue Lights” attended this meeting, which was presided over by George Cabot. A debate in Pennsylvania’s senate opposed this meeting’s proposal to overturn the Three-Fifths Compromise. This meeting was portrayed as treasonous by Democratic-Republicans. For ten points, name this 1815 meeting of New England Federalists.",
      "answer": "Hartford Convention"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1887, this device was the agreed upon solution to the problem that the Gerry Commission tried to resolve. Dentist Albert Southwick was inspired to invent this object after an incident involving a drunken man. Often employed at Sing Sing, this device was used in 1953 on a couple found to have leaked nuclear program secrets to the Soviets. For ten points, name this device used to execute the Rosenbergs, that relies on sending a current through the victim’s body.",
      "answer": "electric chair"
    },
    {
      "question": "Because he could not swim, this man was forced to awkwardly paddle around in water wings when Mao Zedong insisted on meeting in a swimming pool. This leader made a controversial declaration at the Polish Embassy in Moscow, and he protested Lorenzo Sumulong’s address to the UN by banging his shoe on a desk. This man, who denounced the cult of personality of his predecessor in the 1956 “Secret Speech,” presided over the Cuban Missile Crisis. For ten points, name this Soviet premier who succeeded Joseph Stalin in 1953.",
      "answer": "Nikita Khrushchev"
    },
    {
      "question": "The protagonist of this work finds solace in the fact that “his wife and little ones are still beyond the invader’s farthest advance.” At the end of this work, a figure swings “gently from side to side beneath the timbers” of the central location in northern Alabama. The protagonist struggles to free himself of a noose as he falls into the water in, for ten points, what short story about Confederate supporter Peyton Farquhar, written by Ambrose Bierce?",
      "answer": "An Occurrence at Owl Creek Bridge"
    },
    {
      "question": "This university’s Ryerson Physical Laboratory was the site where Robert Millikan conducted his oil drop experiment in 1909. Sergio de Castro became a Minister of Finance after studying at this school as part of the Chile Project. A series of 1962 sit-ins at this university were organized by then-student Bernie Sanders. For ten points, name this university where Milton Friedman was a member of a prominent school of economics in Illinois.",
      "answer": "University of Chicago"
    },
    {
      "question": "This program was aided by the studies of research teams under Bill Moyers and Richard Goodwin. This program was first described in a speech at Ohio University, where it was claimed that “no child will go unfed, and no youngster will go unschooled.” Poll taxes were outlawed under this program’s Voting Rights Act. Medicaid and Medicare were established under, for ten points, what set of domestic welfare programs under Lyndon B. Johnson?",
      "answer": "Great Society"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event produced a list of banned books known as the Index Librorum Prohibitorum and defined the Canon of the Bible to include the whole of the Vulgate and exclude Third and Fourth Maccabees. The papal bull Benedictus Deus upheld the doctrines produced by this meeting, which was presided over by both Julius III and Pius IV. This meeting set the number of sacraments at 7 and condemned the 95 Theses of Martin Luther. For ten points, name this 16th century church council that denounced the Protestant Reformation.",
      "answer": "Council of Trent"
    },
    {
      "question": "This battle was preceded by George Crook’s withdrawal thanks to losses at Rosebud. Frederick Benteen arrived in time to save Marcus Reno’s detachment during this battle, whose losing commander was knocked off his horse by Buffalo Calf Road Woman while his men were surrounded on a hilltop. The 7th Cavalry was annihilated in, for ten points, what 1876 victory for Sitting Bull and Crazy Horse?",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of the Little Bighorn",
        "Custer’s Last Stand",
        "Battle of the Greasy Grass"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this battle, the Marquesa was sent out ahead to prevent attacks from light ships. The fall of the Famagusta colony preceded this battle, which brought an end to one side’s attempt to rescue Cyprus. The Real [ray-AHL] rammed the flagship of Uluc Ali Pasha at the height of this battle. Miguel Cervantes lost an arm in this battle, which was a decisive victory for Don Juan of Austria. For ten points, name this 1571 battle where the Holy League defeated the Ottomans.",
      "answer": "Battle of Lepanto"
    },
    {
      "question": "This treaty was the target of the bull Zelo Domus Dei, in which Pope Innocent X declared it “empty of meaning and effect for all time.” This treaty guaranteed free navigation on the Rhine and reaffirmed the principle of cuius regio, eius religio laid out in the Peace of Augsburg. The Eighty Years’ War was ended as a result of this treaty, which combined negotiations at Osnabruck and Munster. For ten points, name this peace treaty that ended the Thirty Years War.",
      "answer": "Peace of Westphalia"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s most famous endeavor was thwarted by Executive Order 1111, which placed his officers under federal control. After this man refused to listen to Attorney General Nicholas Katzenbach, he was confronted by Henry Graham when John F. Kennedy called up the National Guard. This man opposed James Hood and Vivian Malone at the Foster Auditorium after declaring his support for “segregation forever.” For ten points, name this governor of Alabama who made the “stand in the schoolhouse door” in 1963.",
      "answer": "George Wallace"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this battle, Everett Peabody lost his life trying to hold off oncoming Confederates that other Union commanders were unable to detect. Benjamin Prentiss was one of the Union commanders at this battle, where Don Carlos Buell separated his Army of the Ohio into four divisions. P.G.T. Beauregard took command of the Confederate troops after Albert Sidney Johnston became the highest ranking officer to die in the Civil War in, for ten points, what 1862 battle where heavy fighting took place along the Hornet’s Nest in Tennessee?",
      "answer": "Battle of Shiloh"
    },
    {
      "question": "This battle featured fierce fighting over the village of Ponyri, which gave one side the opportunity to launch Operation Kutuzov. Walther Model and Erich von Manstein aimed to pincer the namesake salient during this battle. Codenamed Citadel, this battle was delayed so that one side could wait for more Panthers. Tigers and T-34s clashed at Prokhorovka in, for ten points, what 1943 battle on the Eastern Front, the largest tank battle in history?",
      "answer": "Battle of Kursk"
    },
    {
      "question": "While surveying the grounds for this project, its architect crushed his foot when it was trapped by a passing ferry, resulting in a tetanus infection that killed him. A physician involved in the creation of this project named Andrew Smith coined the name of a sickness that afflicted many of the workers along it, “caisson disease.” This project began in 1869 and was opened in 1883 as Chester Arthur walked along it. Washington Roebling oversaw the creation of, for ten points, what bridge connecting Manhattan to a namesake New York borough?",
      "answer": "Brooklyn Bridge"
    },
    {
      "question": "The majority opinion in this case cites Pugsley v. Sellmeyer when noting that it “does not relate to regulation of the length of skirts or the type of clothing.” Abe Fortas delivered the majority opinion in this case, which argued that “the petitioners were quiet and passive.” This case arose out of demonstrations in support of the Christmas Truce. This case’s namesake test has been used to see if school policies violate constitutional rights. For ten points, name this 1969 case about a ban on the wearing of black armbands to protest the Vietnam War.",
      "answer": "Tinker v. Des Moines"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was accused of having “undertaken to be the hero of the night” among a group described as a “motley rabble of saucy boys.” This man, who is buried in the Old Granary Burying Ground, was once thought to have been a slave of William Brown. A protest against the Townshend Acts ended with the death of this man, followed by four other deaths; their killers were defended by John Adams. For ten points, name this black man who was the first to die in the Boston Massacre.",
      "answer": "Crispus Attucks"
    },
    {
      "question": "After serving as a Confederate soldier at the Battle of Shiloh, this man joined the Union Army at the behest of James Mulligan. When this man heard that an officer in his “Rear Guard” handed over a girl to be eaten by cannibals, he attempted to place the blame on trader Tippu Tip; that incident occurred while he led an expedition to relieve Emin Pasha. In 1869, this man was sent to relieve a Scottish missionary who was searching for the source of the Nile. For ten points, name this explorer who legendarily asked “Dr. Livingstone, I presume?”",
      "answer": "Henry Morton Stanley"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler won battles at the Hellespont and Chrysopolis to put down a revolt led by Licinius. At one battle, this man claimed he saw a Chi-Rho in the sky with the words “in this sign, you will conquer.” Maxentius was defeated by this man at the Battle of Milvian Bridge. The Edict of Milan, which granted tolerance to Christians, was issued by this emperor. For ten points, name this “Great” Roman Emperor, the first to convert to Christianity.",
      "answer": [
        "Constantine the Great",
        "Constantine I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A player of this instrument who died at a young age due to multiple sclerosis was married to conductor Daniel Barenboim. This is the main instrument of the founder of the Silkroad ensemble and arts non-profit. On the day that Soviet troops invaded Czechoslovakia to end the Prague Spring, Dvorak’s B minor concerto for this instrument was performed by Mstislav Rostropovich. Jacqueline du Pr´e and Yo-Yo Ma play, for ten points, what large string instrument?",
      "answer": "cello"
    },
    {
      "question": "A fleet of 49 ships on the victorious side of this battle was commanded by Charles Saunders. Members of the 78th Highlanders were able to make a surprise landing the night before this battle because one side was expecting a supply convoy. A general at this battle claimed that only 100 men were needed to guard L’Anse au Foulon. For ten points, name this battle in the Canadian theater of the Seven Years’ War where the Marquis de Montcalm and James Wolfe, the generals of the opposing sides, were both killed.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Quebec",
        "Battle of the Plains of Abraham"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A disaster at this site forced nearby residents to move to the newly constructed city of Slavutych and prompted the construction of an iron sarcophagus to enclose this site. Sweden experienced an incidence of acid rain after a disaster at this site, which is now part of a zone of alienation. The Red Forest was created and Pripyat, Ukraine was rendered uninhabitable by the failure of, for ten points, what Soviet nuclear power plant that melted down in 1986?",
      "answer": "Chernobyl Nuclear Power Plant"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this war, two generals played a board game called petteia while, unknown to them, a battle raged around them. The Phrygian king Teleutas died in single combat during this war while fighting Ajax, son of Telamon. To avoid fighting in this war, a man pretended to be senile and plowed his field with salt, but gave up the ruse by swerving to avoid his baby son, Telemachus. For ten points, name this ancient war, the subject of Homer’s Iliad.",
      "answer": "Trojan War"
    },
    {
      "question": "A weapon that made use of this object was conceptualized by Hermann Oberth and was studied by Nazi engineers at Hillersleben who predicted they could build it within 100 years. A large black stone in reverence to this object was taken to the Palatine Hill by Elagabalus, whose name derives from a cult surrounding this object. During the siege of Syracuse, Archimedes designed a “death ray” that used this body to destroy enemy ships through concentrated heat. Louis the 14th was nicknamed the king of, for ten points, what star?",
      "answer": "the Sun"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader’s cause was damaged by constant feuds with Li Zongren over control of the army. This man was forced to form the Second United Front with his enemies after he was kidnapped in the Xi’an [shee-ahn] incident. This man’s wife, Soong Mei-Ling, tried to promote the “four virtues” during the New Life Movement. For ten points, name this successor of Sun Yat-sen, a Kuomintang leader who set up his base in Taiwan after losing the Chinese Civil War.",
      "answer": [
        "Chiang Kai-Shek",
        "Jiang Jieshi"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Gabriel tries to play this instrument, but it makes no sound, at the end of Fences by August Wilson. In 1845, Christophe Ballot assembled two groups of players of this instrument for what may have been the first public demonstration of the Doppler Effect. The “natural” style of this instrument was popular in the Baroque era, and this instrument didn’t receive its now-common valves until the 20th century. Marching parades and fanfares typically feature, for ten points, what highest standard brass instrument?",
      "answer": "trumpet"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man yelled “Come on, you Wolverines” to rally the Michigan Cavalry Brigade, which he commanded at Hanover and at Gettysburg during the Civil War. Prior to one battle, Alfred Terry ordered this commander of the 7th Cavalry Regiment to scout along the Rosebud Creek. Forces led by Chief Gall and Crazy Horse killed this commander and his companies at an 1876 battle during the Great Sioux War. For ten points, name this officer who made his “last stand” at the Battle of Little Bighorn.",
      "answer": "George Armstrong Custer"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this event, the Twa people were targeted for allegedly aiding the enemy. The Arusha Accords failed to address the tensions leading up to this event, which was mitigated through Operation Turquoise’s creation of a safe zone. The order to “cut down the tall trees” was given during this event, which was perpetrated by the Interahamwe. A Patriotic Front led by Paul Kagame took Kigali to end, for ten points, what 1994 event in which the Hutus slaughtered the Tutsis?",
      "answer": [
        "Rwandan genocide",
        "descriptive answers of a genocide of the Tutsis/by the Hutus before either is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An 1897 book titled for this action claims that it is more common during peace than war and examines historical rates of this action for Protestants and Catholics. This action is divided into egoistic, altruistic, anomic, and fatalistic types in one of the first ever sociological case studies. Emile Durkheim studied, for ten points, what action that may be taken as a result of severe depression, the act of ending one’s own life?",
      "answer": [
        "suicide",
        "obvious equivalents such as killing yourself before “ending your own life”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Fundraising for this monument included the creation of 5 million half-dollar coins that depicted two chatting soldiers on horseback. North Carolina governor Angus McLean offered protection from extradition to Gutzon Borglum, who fled arrest in 1925 after being fired from the design of this monument and destroying his models. This monument, the world’s largest bas relief, is the centerpiece of a park that opened on the 100th anniversary of Abraham Lincoln’s assassination. For ten points, name this controversial Georgia monument that honors three Confederate leaders.",
      "answer": "Stone Mountain"
    },
    {
      "question": "Joseph Rosa is considered the chief biographer of this man, who allegedly killed a bear with a knife to allow a freight train to continue its journey to Santa Fe. This man killed the leader of the McCanles Gang during a fight at a Pony Express Station. Hays and Abilene were the Kansas cities where this man served as marshal. Jack McCall murdered this man at a saloon in Deadwood while he held two black eights and two black aces during a game of poker. For ten points, name this Wild West folk hero known for carrying the “dead man’s hand.”",
      "answer": "James Butler “Wild Bill” Hickok"
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization faced a rebellion of miners led by the nobleman Engelbrekt, who called the first Riksdag of all four estates to rally opposition. The members of this organization were unified in their opposition to Albrecht of Mecklenburg, though they later allowed his son Erik of Pomerania to rule over this group. This union was formed in order to counteract the Hanseatic League by Margaret I. For ten points, name this union of Denmark, Sweden, and Norway that lasted from 1397 to 1523.",
      "answer": "Kalmar Union"
    },
    {
      "question": "During the Civil War, cannons named for these people were nothing more than disguised logs. Members of this group included abolitionist Anthony Benezet and a “Fighting” major general who lost the Battle of Guilford Courthouse. Nathanael Greene was a member of this religious group, which was founded by George Fox. For ten points, name this pacifist religious group, also called the Society of Friends, whose members included William Penn.",
      "answer": [
        "Quakers",
        "Society of Friends before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler was adopted by the empress Ruqaiya after a soothsayer claimed he would be a great ruler. This man was forced to watch his sons fight for his kingdom at Samurgh after an illness led Dara Shikoh to be named regent. In his final years, this man was confined in the Red Fort, which he had built. This father of Aurangzeb became known for constructing a white mausoleum for his wife, Mumtaz. For ten points, name this Mughal emperor who built the Taj Mahal.",
      "answer": "Shah Jahan"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man deposed Alakeshwara of the Kotte Kingdom during a military expedition to Ceylon. He helped oversee the construction of the Porcelain Tower after he was reassigned as commander of Nanjing, after his influence waned under Hongxi [hong-shee]. This man’s most famous feats were performed under the Yongle Emperor, to whose court he brought a Malindi giraffe. For ten points, name this admiral of the Ming Dynasty known for his seven “treasure voyages.”",
      "answer": "Zheng He , but be lenient"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man heavily used the theme “Ashokan Farewell” in one of his works. This man focused on people like Everett Alvarez, Ambassador Bui Diem, and Tim O’Brien in a ten episode work that features his trademark style of slowly zooming away from a still image. Mathew Brady’s photographs and David McCulloch’s narration were praised in a 1990 work by, for ten points, what director of The Vietnam War, The Civil War, and several other documentary miniseries for television?",
      "answer": "Ken Burns"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ship was sent to patrol the Burdwood Bank on what would be its final mission. This ship was formally commissioned as the USS Phoenix, but was eventually sold off for the People’s Loyalty Day celebration. After this ship was sunk, The Sun published an infamous headline that read “Our lads sink gunboat and hole cruiser.” The “Gotcha!” headline trumpeted the sinking of this ship, the first ever to be sunk by a nuclear submarine. A general who fought for Argentine independence names, for ten points, what ship that was sunk during the Falklands War?",
      "answer": "ARA General Belgrano"
    },
    {
      "question": "Members of this general profession like Yuri Kondratyuk [[kon-DRAT-yuk]] and Vladimir Myasishchev [[my-ah-SISS-tchoff]] worked in locations called sharashkas in Soviet gulags. The so-called \"Layer Cake\" idea by a member of this profession led to the development of the RDS-37. Trofim Lysenko created fraudulent theories while working in this profession. The activist Andrei Sakharov [[SOCK-ar-off]] held, for ten points, what general profession, practitioners of which designed the Tsar Bomba?",
      "answer": "Scientist"
    },
    {
      "question": "One person of this type, named Isaac Friend, planned a failed insurrection in York County, Virginia. Thomas Grantham put down a rebellion fueled in part by people with this status. Some English prisoners of war were forced into this condition, while many immigrants voluntarily entered into it. During Bacon’s Rebellion, many of these people revolted against the colonial elite. For ten points, name these workers who entered into voluntary servitude.",
      "answer": [
        "Indentured servants",
        ","
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "John Walter Bratton composed a song about a picnic held by these objects. A trip with Governor Andrew Longino inspired these items, which were exported to the US in the 55 PB form by Alban Berg's brother, Hermann. Morris Michtom and Richard Steiff created these toys which were inspired by a Clifford Berryman cartoon showing a hunter refusing to kill a tied up animal with the words \"Drawing the Line in Mississippi.” For ten points, name these stuffed toys named for Theodore Roosevelt.",
      "answer": "Teddy Bears"
    },
    {
      "question": "Galen believed these people were dominated by blood humor and red choler, unlike others who had an excess of black choler or phlegm. These people play in the Scottish poem \"Rait's Raving.” Only under Victorian law was the labor of these people restricted as, for much of history, these people were seen as simply smaller versions of adults. Canon law in medieval England stated this period in human development ended at age 12. For ten points, name this period before adolescence.",
      "answer": [
        "Children",
        "answers such as Childhood indicating the period of human development prior to adulthood"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Oprah Winfrey and this man are producing a series on mental health for Apple TV+, and this man launched an orphans' charity called Sentebale. The Taliban threatened to kidnap or kill this man while he was at Camp Bastion in Afghanistan. This man was once photographed at Highgrove House wearing an Afrika Korps uniform. With his wife, this man founded Archewell, Inc. for creative media ventures. The brother of Prince William and the son of Princess Diana, for ten points, name this prince who is married to Meghan Markle.",
      "answer": [
        "Prince Harry",
        "Duke of Sussex",
        "Henry"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This person’s namesake charitable foundation was started after the Sociedad de Beneficencia refused her support due to her past career as an actress. A city built by that foundation was temporarily renamed Ciudad General Martín Miguel de Güemes following a coup d’etat which removed this woman’s husband from power. The title “Spiritual Leader of the Nation” was given to, for ten points, what women’s suffrage activist and supporter of the descamisados, a former First Lady of Argentina?",
      "answer": [
        "Eva Perón",
        "Evita with",
        "without surname"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The first of these episodes in recorded history was initiated by artisans working on the necropolis of King Ramses III. In 1894, Eugene Debs received a prison sentence when his constituents carrying out this action disobeyed a government injunction not to interfere with mail trains. One of these events ended in 1981 when the Reagan administration fired air traffic controllers involved in this action. For ten points, name these actions coordinated by employees who refuse to work.",
      "answer": "Labor strikes"
    },
    {
      "question": "A monument at this site erected by the United Daughters of the Confederacy was controversial for its depiction of the \"faithful slave,\" Heyward Shepherd. Before his execution, the leader of an event at this site noted that \"the crimes of this guilty land will never be purged away, but with Blood.\" By seizing arms at this site, the leader of the Pottawatomie Massacre hoped to spark a slave revolt. For ten points, name this West Virginia town where John Brown raided a federal arsenal.",
      "answer": "Harpers Ferry Armory, West Virginia"
    },
    {
      "question": "This person's painting, \"Yucca and Cactus,\" was shown at the 1893 Columbian Exposition. This innovator’s \"bulletins\" helped farmers grow crops like cotton and sweet potatoes. This man combatted boll weevil infestation through crop rotation, which led Time magazine to give him the nickname, the \"Black Leonardo.” At an Alabama institution, this man pioneered products like antiseptic hair dressing made from peanut oil. For ten points, name this inventor who worked at Tuskegee Institute.",
      "answer": "George Washington Carver"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 773, this man led a campaign against the Saxons, during which he forced the Engrians to tear down the pagan Irminsul pillar and convert to Christianity. Upon this man’s death and burial at Aachen, his son Louis the Pious took the throne. Pope Leo III rejected the legitimacy of Empress Irene of Constantinople when he crowned this man Imperator Romanorum at St. Peter’s Basilica in 800. For ten points, name this man, who in 768 became King of the Franks following the death of Pepin the Short.",
      "answer": [
        "Charlemagne",
        "Charles the Great"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An ultranationalist group named for blue examples of these objects supported Chiang Kai-Shek’s New Life Movement. The Expedition of the Thousand was conducted by the Red [these objects], who followed Giuseppe Garibaldi. A 1922 March on Rome was led by Benito Mussolini and his followers, nicknamed for black [objects of this type]. For ten points, name this article of clothing whose “Brown” types were worn by the SA [[ESS-AY]].",
      "answer": [
        "Shirts [",
        "Blue Shirts",
        "Red Shirts",
        "Black Shirts",
        "Brown Shirts"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's father formed a short-lived alliance with Murad II until he was imprisoned. This man and his brother Radu were jailed as children, though the Ottomans released him after an invasion of his homeland by John Hunyadi. The envoys of this man's childhood friend, Sultan Mehmed II, were impaled on stakes by this voivode [[VOY-vohd]]. The ruler of independent Wallachia [[woh-LEH-kyuh]] and a Romanian national hero was, for ten points, what infamous warlord who inspired a vampire created by Bram Stoker?",
      "answer": [
        "Vlad the Impaler or Vlad Tepes ]",
        "Vlad III",
        "Vlad Dracula",
        "or Vlad Drăculea"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man piloted a Gonzalo Coelho [[koo-EL-hoh]] voyage to Brazil which encountered its discoverer, Pedro Cabral. This Florentine worked for merchant Gianotto Berardi, who was an early investor in the 1492 Columbus expedition. The cartographer Martin Waldseemüller [[VAHLD-zee-MEW-luh]] was influenced by the Soderini letter to name a landmass for this explorer. For ten points, what Italian navigator, who is credited with coining the term \"New World, is the namesake of two continents in the western hemisphere?",
      "answer": "Amerigo Vespucci"
    },
    {
      "question": "Dirt brought from this state was used to bury the Marquis [[mahr-KEE]] de Lafayette in Paris. The storming of this state's Springfield Armory occurred during Shays' Rebellion, an uprising of disenchanted Revolutionary War veterans. Israel Putnam legendarily said \"Don't fire 'til you see the whites of their eyes\" at a 1775 engagement with the Redcoats in this state. The Battle of Bunker Hill occurred in, for ten points, what New England state?",
      "answer": "Massachusetts"
    },
    {
      "question": "Roy Choi created a popular variety of these objects in southern California known as Kogi. A variety of these objects that often frequent construction sites are known as “roach coaches.” In accordance with its roots, a popular New England variety of these objects called Roxy’s sells a product known as the Green Muenster. These objects may have grown out of the chuck wagon. In the 1970s, Raul Martinez pioneered the use of these objects to sell tacos. For ten points, name these vehicles where one can grab a meal.",
      "answer": "Food Trucks"
    },
    {
      "question": "In Islamic tradition, this figure will kill the malevolent ad-Dajjal [[ahd-dah-JAHL]] and both Gog and Magog during the Second Coming. The Cathedral of Turin houses a shroud supposedly bearing the face of this man, whose execution apparatus was split into several pieces that are considered relics in the Christian church. For ten points, name this holy figure who was executed under Roman law in Judea, being nailed to the True Cross.",
      "answer": [
        "Jesus Christ",
        "either underlined portion",
        "Isa ibn Maryam",
        "or Yeshua bar Joseph"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "John Hyrcanus [[heer-KAH-nooss]] subjugated and converted Itureans [[\"eye\"-TOO- ree-ans]] to this faith after a prolonged campaign. Two scholars of this faith who convinced the Himyarite [[HIM-yah-rite]] king Abu Karib to lift his siege of Yathrib later facilitated his conversion to this faith. The kingdom of Judah's fall to Nebuchadnezzar's [[NEH-boo-kahd- ZEH-zars]] forces led to a period experienced by this faith's adherents known as the Babylonian Captivity. For ten points, name this dominant faith of the Israelites.",
      "answer": [
        "Judaism",
        "Jewish Faith",
        "or Jews"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In her twenties, this chemistry teacher worked at Chicago’s Hull House, before attending the Wharton School. As head of the National Consumers' League, this woman witnessed the Triangle Shirtwaist Factory Fire, leading to her appointment to the Committee of Safety. With a first lady, this woman organized the She-She-She camps in her highest office. For ten points, name this first female cabinet member, the Secretary of Labor under Franklin D. Roosevelt.",
      "answer": "Frances Perkins or Fannie Coralie Perkins"
    },
    {
      "question": "Pausanias [[pow-SAN-ee-uss]] reported that the polis of Thebes claimed to have the bones of this hero. Roland's legendary sword Durendal was first forged for this man. Neoptolemus [[nee-op-TAH-leh-muss]] supposedly killed this man's infant son, Astyanax, by throwing him from the walls of a citadel. This man slew Patroclus while wearing the armor of his shield-brother. Achilles dragged the corpse of, for ten points, which Trojan hero and son of Priam?",
      "answer": "Hector"
    },
    {
      "question": "Akbar the Great ordered a Persian language version of this work be produced known as the Razmnama [[rah-zem-NAH-mah]], which translates to \"Book of War.\" In this work, a lengthy journey of exile to the Himalayas leads to the death of Draupadi. The Pandava and Kaurava families clash in this work's Kurukshetra War, following a failed peace conference led by Krishna. For ten points, name this Hindu epic written in Sanskrit which contains the Bhagavad Gita.",
      "answer": "Mahabharata ]"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A founder of one of these parties in Italy argued states maintain power through controlling culture in his Prison Notebooks. Parties by this name were instructed to join Popular Fronts during the 1930s to oppose fascism. This party is still the dominant political party in Laos and Vietnam. For 10 points, name these parties promoting the theories of Karl Marx.",
        "answer": "Communist parties"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Yugoslav leader took his country out of Cominform after a dispute with the Soviet Union over the Greek civil war?",
        "answer": "Josip Broz Tito"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This group was heavily advised by future Pennsylvania Senator Arlen Specter. Its members included Allen Dulles and Hale Boggs, and it was criticized for advocating the \"magic bullet\" theory. This group was led by the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court and concluded that Oswald acted alone. For 10 points, name this body charged with investigating the Kennedy assassination.",
        "answer": "Warren Commission"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Warren Commission viewed what clothing salesman's thirty-second home movie of the shooting?",
        "answer": "Abraham Zapruder"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This animal is believed to give the \"five products\" including gobar, an energy source. The tilak mark is often made from the excrement of these animals, which are the subject of the holiday Gopastami. Killing these animals was prohibited by the Vedas, and they are now a major cause of traffic hindrance in Delhi. For 10 points, name these animals sacred to Hindus.",
        "answer": "cows"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Hindu destroyer god rides Nandi, the \"bull of heaven?\"",
        "answer": "Shiva"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Bernard de Launay was killed during this event. It was lead by Pierre-Augustin Hulin, and partially sparked by the dismissal of the finance minister Jacques Necker three days before. Celebrated on a holiday observed on July 14, this event liberated a mere seven prisoners. For 10 points, name this 1789 event in which an angry mob sacked a Parisian prison.",
        "answer": "storming of the Bastille"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What earlier resident of the Bastille wrote Candide (can-DEED)?",
        "answer": "Voltaire"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Subgroups called iwi divided these people, who argued based on language differences that they never meant to cede sovereignty to William Hobson in the 1840 Treaty of Waitangi. Hone Heke was a chief of these people. Some of their men mark themselves with swirling lines of ta moko, a type of carved-in ink tattoo. For 10 points, name these indigenous inhabitants of New Zealand.",
        "answer": "Maōri people"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Western weapon, a descendant of the arquebus, was first traded to the Ngapuhi iwi in 1807, kicking off a set of namesake \"wars\" on North Island?",
        "answer": "muskets"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1992, this agency launched a program to certify electronic devices, most visibly computer monitors, as efficient, known as EnergyStar. A program administered by this government agency has targeted sites such as Love Canal and is known as Superfund. For 10 points, name this agency created by Richard Nixon that enforces the Clean Water Act and similar laws.",
        "answer": "EPA"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Love Canal crisis occurred during the Presidency of what man, who also installed solar panels on the roof of the White House?",
        "answer": "Jimmy Carter"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "James Nasmyth used six-way indexing to perfect precision milling, a key component of this idea. Eli Terry applied this concept to clock manufacture in 1814, and it was greatly refined in 1803 by Marc Brunel. For 10 points, identify this manufacturing concept pioneered in gunsmithing by Eli Whitney, in which components across a production run are identical.",
        "answer": "interchangeable parts"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Eli Whitney obtained an army contract to make muskets just as the \"Quasi-War,\" an undeclared naval war with what country, was beginning in 1798?",
        "answer": "France"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The first prototype of these objects was constructed by William Foster & Co., and nicknamed Little Willie. Modified versions of these objects, including Crocodiles and Crabs, carried flails and laid bridges and were named Hobart’s Funnies. The Landship Commission developed the Mark line of these objects, which were first used in the Battle of Cambrai. Developed in response to stagnant trench warfare in WWI, for ten points, what vehicles, such as the M4 Sherman, use tracks instead of wheels and have a lot of armor?",
        "answer": [
          "Tanks",
          "landships before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hobart’s Funnies were, like Mulberry harbors, designed after the failed Dieppe Raid to meet the challenges of this 1944 invasion in Northern France.",
        "answer": "Invasion of Normandy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this show’s third season, an Aqua Net design showing four people riding in a convertible has to be remade following the John F. Kennedy assassination. This show’s protagonist assumes his commanding officer’s identity during the Korean War, and discusses the meaning of nostalgia while delivering a sales pitch for the Kodak Carousel slide projector. For ten points, name this recently-ended AMC drama starring Jon Hamm as 1960s advertising executive Don Draper.",
        "answer": "Mad Men"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The final episode of Mad Men closes with the real-life 1971 “Hilltop” commercial, in which a group of young people sing that they would “like to buy the world” this popular beverage.",
        "answer": [
          "Coca-Cola",
          "Coke"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these people, Jean [ZHAHN] Calas, was unjustly accused of the murder of his son and was the subject of a work by Voltaire. These people were welcomed by Frederick William of Brandenburg in the Edict of Potsdam, and the Duke of Buckingham attempted to aid these people at the Siege of La Rochelle. One of their leaders, Gaspard de Coligny, was assassinated during an event targeting them, which occurred after the marriage of Marguerite and a king of Navarre. Henry IV led, for ten points, what religious dissidents in France, who were targeted in the St. Bartholomew’s Day Massacre?",
        "answer": "Huguenots"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Siege of the Huguenot stronghold of La Rochelle was led by what minister to Louis XIII, nicknamed the Red Eminence?",
        "answer": "Jean Armand du Plessis, Cardinal de Richelieu"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s son James was killed by members of the Shawnee tribe, sparking Dunmore’s War, and his son Israel was killed at the Battle of Blue Licks. This friend of Simon Kenton was briefly captured by Blackfish in 1778. A John Filson book created a series of myths about, for ten points, what frontiersman who helped settle Kentucky by blazing a trail through the Cumberland Gap?",
        "answer": "Daniel Boone"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Daniel Boone blazed this road through the Cumberland Gap to link Kentucky to the east.",
        "answer": "Wilderness Road"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Hannibal’s War, also known as the Torstensson War, was a subsidiary of this larger conflict, which saw Christian IV of Denmark sign the Treaty of Lu¨beck after being defeated by Albrecht von Wallenstein. Frederick V was deposed after the Battle of White Mountain early in this war, which saw one side win the battle of Lu¨tzen despite the death of their king, who had earlier defeated Count Tilly at the Battle of Breitenfeld. Gustavus Adolphus died in, for ten points, what war, largely between Protestant and Catholic alliances?",
        "answer": "Thirty Years’ War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Thirty Years War was in part precipitated by what event, where two Austrian diplomats were thrown into a pile of horse manure in Bohemia?",
        "answer": "Second Defenestration of Prague"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Key insight into the cause of this event was provided by the Strubbe Tape. Glenn Frank prevented violent retaliation against the perpetrators off this event, which was sparked by opposition to the invasion of Cambodia. Mary Ann Vecchio’s screaming over Jeffrey Miller’s dead body was captured in an iconic photograph after, for ten points, what massacre of four students by the Ohio National Guard in 1970?",
        "answer": [
          "Kent State shootings or Kent State massacre",
          "equivalents"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Two days prior to the shooting, protesters set fire to a building for this military program, which trains officers at colleges and universities.",
        "answer": "Reserve Officers’ Training Corps or ROTC"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Albert of Mainz’s desire for cathedrals prompted the writing of this document, which was anticipated by a similar document written by Andreas Karlstadt. It ends by casting away prophets who say “Peace, peace!” without providing peace. The papal bull Exsurge Domine [ex-oor-gay doh-me-nay] identified 41 mistakes in this work. For ten points, name this list of complaints directed towards the Catholic Church and its policy of indulgences that was apocryphally nailed to a door in Wittenberg by Martin Luther.",
        "answer": "95 Theses"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "At this imperial diet in 1521, Martin Luther supposedly claimed “Here I stand; I can do no other” while standing up to Charles V. Johann Eck debated Luther at this meeting.",
        "answer": "Diet of Worms"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s commander, Hudhayfah ibn Mihsan, assisted his campaign against apostasy known as the Ridda Wars. After hundreds of hafizes were killed at the Battle of Yamama, this ruler, called “the Truthful,” ordered the collection of the verses of the Qu’ran. For ten points, name this companion of Muhammad who directly succeeded him as the first of the “rightly guided” caliphs.",
        "answer": "Abu Bakr or Abdullah ibn Abi Quhafa"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A hafiz is a Muslim who has completed this task, necessary for preservation of the Qur’an prior to Abu Bakr’s work.",
        "answer": "memorize the entire Qur’an"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Daniel Mendoza introduced defensive movement into this sport in the late 18th century, and John Douglas, Marquess of Queensbury, decreased violence in this sport with new rules in the 19th century. The retired James Jeffries was hailed as a “Great White Hope” to defeat James Johnson, a black champion of this sport in 1910. Another champion of this sport refused to join the military during the Vietnam War, citing his Muslim beliefs. For ten points, name this sport whose champions have included Muhammad Ali.",
        "answer": "boxing"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the 1974 Rumble in the Jungle, Muhammad Ali defeated this grilling entrepreneur to regain the world heavyweight championship.",
        "answer": "George Foreman"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Hosius of Cordoba led the synod that called for the convention of this council, which rejected the Quartodecimans’ dating of Easter. A conflict with the Church of the Martyrs, known as the Meletian schism, was addressed at this meeting, which was convened by Constantine I in 325 AD. For ten points, namethisearlychurchcouncilwhichproclaimedabeliefinGod, Jesus, andtheHolySpiritinitsnamesake “Creed.”",
        "answer": "First Council of Nicaea"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This controversy was denounced at the First Council of Nicaea. Propounded by its namesake Alexandrine priest, this doctrine placed the Son subordinate to the Father.",
        "answer": [
          "Arianism",
          "the Arian Controversy"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "James Blaine and Robert Todd Lincoln were witnesses to this event, which took place in the Baltimore and Potomac Railroad Station. The perpetrator of this crime chose a revolver for its ivory handle, which would look good in a museum. The victim of this event survived for over two months, despite the summer heat and incompetent doctors, before he died and was succeeded by a Stalwart. For ten points, name this 1881 crime, committed by Charles Guiteau [ghee-toe], which elevated Chester Arthur to the presidency.",
        "answer": "assassination of James Garfield"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This inventor of the telephone tried to use a rudimentary metal detector to find the bullet in Garfield’s body.",
        "answer": "Alexander Graham Bell"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This action was achieved via the Instrument of Accession, developed by Lord Mountbatten. The Radcliffe Line’s establishment preceding this event led to mass incidents of inter-religious violence. Nathuram Godse assassinated a prominent opponent of this action before it took place. Muhammad Ali Jinnah led the Muslim League during this process, in which violence racked in the provinces of Jammu and Kashmir. Twelve million people were displaced as a result of, for ten points, what splitting of the former British Raj into Muslim and Hindu states?",
        "answer": [
          "partition of India",
          "equivalent descriptions, such as the division of Pakistan and India"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Jawaharlal Nehru’s “Tryst with Destiny,” speech delivered during the Partition, invoked the stroke of this specific moment when the Partition formally occurred. In a 1981 novel, Saleem Sinai is born at this moment.",
        "answer": [
          "midnight on August 15, 1947",
          "Midnight’s Children"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one episode, this show’s protagonist tells the audience that General Longstreet died for “sitting too high on his horse” during a reenactment of the Battle of the Wilderness. The protagonist of this show has his career jeopardized when his wife, played by Robin Wright, leaves him prior to the New Hampshire primary. For ten points, name this series about Frank Underwood, a ruthless politician played by Kevin Spacey, which is produced and distributed by Netflix.",
        "answer": "House of Cards"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Frank Underwood attended a military academy in South Carolina before going to Harvard Law School. Name either the fictional academy in the show or the real-life academy on which it is based.",
        "answer": [
          "The Sentinel",
          "The Citadel, The Military College of South Carolina"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A commercial for this company featured David Graham speaking to a seated, motionless audience as Anya Major runs from police. This company’s rush to release a product with a GUI, or graphical user interface, ended with the failed Lisa in 1983 and, a year later, the more successful Macintosh, promoted by the “1984” Super Bowl commercial. The iMac was developed by, for ten points, what personal computing company co-founded by Steve Wozniak and Steve Jobs?",
        "answer": "Apple Computer Inc."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The “1984” ad can be interpreted as an attack on the ubiquity of this Apple rival, known as “Big Blue.”",
        "answer": "IBM or International Business Machines Corporation"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man launched an attack at Targoviste in an attempt to assassinate an enemy ruler. After negotiations stalled, this man was captured by Matthias Corvinus and eventually released to his homeland. After failing to pay the jizya tax on non-Muslims, this ruler executed two envoys of Mehmed II, leading to an Ottoman conquest of his lands. For ten points, name this Prince of Wallachia known for driving stakes through his enemies.",
        "answer": [
          "Vlad the Impaler or Vlad III of Wallachia",
          "Vlad Dracula",
          "Vlad Tepes"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Matthias Corvinus was the son of Janos Hunyadi and ruler of this kingdom to the west of Wallachia. Corvinus ruled and lived in this kingdom’s Buda Castle.",
        "answer": "Hungary"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A speech given at this location during a “refulgent summer” claims that “the word Miracle, as pronounced by Christian churches, gives a false impression; it is Monster;” that speech was controversially given to a group of young Unitarians at this school, which was later secularized by Charles Eliot. In 1838, a glimpse into Transcendentalist philosophy was given to the Divinity School at, for ten points, what elite university in Cambridge, Massachusetts?",
        "answer": [
          "Harvard University",
          "Harvard Divinity School"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Transcendentalist delivered the Divinity School Address.",
        "answer": "Ralph Waldo Emerson"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this battle, John Gordon noted that he had fought his troops “to a frazzle” and required heavy support from James Longstreet. The winning commander in this skirmish was afflicted with a migraine until he received word that the fighting was over; shortly after, Wilmer McLean’s house served as a meeting place. For ten points, name this Civil War battle that took place on the morning of April 9, 1865, a few hours before Ulysses Grant accepted Robert E. Lee’s surrender, effectively ending the war.",
        "answer": "Battle of Appomattox Court House"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ironically, Wilmer McLean moved his family to Appomattox to avoid the war; his farmland had been the site of this early battle of the war.",
        "answer": "First Battle of Bull Run or First Battle of Manassas"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was put in charge of an economic and rearmament program called the Four Year Plan. This man’s chief of staff, Karl Koller, convinced him to write a telegram asking for a transfer of power. After the failure of Eagle Day, a large air assault ordered by this man, he began a system of strategic bombing called the Blitz. This man committed suicide the day before his execution, which had been ordered by the Nuremberg Trials. For ten points, name this head of the Luftwaffe and right hand man of Adolf Hitler.",
        "answer": "Hermann G¨oring"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "G¨oring created this Nazi paramilitary group, nicknamed the Brownshirts. They supported Hitler’s rise in the 1920s and were succeeded by the SS after the Night of the Long Knives.",
        "answer": "SA or Sturmabteilung"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this event, Dudley Field Malone claimed that there is no such thing as “a duel with the truth.” The veracity of the Book of Genesis was questioned in this event, which responded to a violation of the Butler Act. The defense in this trial was led by Clarence Darrow, while the prosecutor was William Jennings Bryan. For ten points, name this 1925 Tennessee court case focusing on a high school teacher who illegally taught evolution.",
        "answer": [
          "Scopes Monkey Trial",
          "State of Tennessee v. Scopes"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Scopes trial inspired Jerome Lawrence and Robert Edwin Lee to write this 1955 play. Like Arthur Miller’s The Crucible, this play served as an allegory for the ongoing Red Scare.",
        "answer": "Inherit the Wind"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1642, this man landed at what is now Macquarie Harbor, making its first European discovery. During this man’s 1643-44 voyage to find a passage to Chile south of the normal trade route, he mistook the west coast of New Zealand’s North Island as the west coast of Australia, thought the Cook Strait was a bay, and missed mainland Australia entirely. For ten points, name this Dutch explorer and namesake of an Australian island state.",
        "answer": "Abel Tasman"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "While Tasman’s boats were floundering around New Zealand, one of them was attacked by a group of these indigenous people of New Zealand.",
        "answer": "Maori people"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event may have been planned at the “Monday Night Meeting” by George Engel. The word “Ruhe” was supposedly used as a codeword to signal this event, in which police officer Mathias Degan was killed. Anarchist Albert Parsons surrendered after this event, which was held in front of McCormick Harvesting Company by strikers hoping for 8 hour workdays. August Spies was executed for his role in, for ten points, what 1886 bombing and ensuing riot, a turning point of the labor movement?",
        "answer": "Haymarket Square riot or bombing, affair, etc."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Haymarket Square riot took place in this state. Its governor, John Peter Altgeld, eventually pardoned three of the convicted anarchists.",
        "answer": "Illinois"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A Sangaku problem presented on a 1824 tablet in the Gunma prefecture concerns three of these shapes touching. These shapes were defined by Apollonius as the set of points in the plane that have a fixed ratio of distances to two foci. When Ferdinand von Lindemann proved that a certain constant is transcendental, he proved it is impossible to “square” one of these shapes. Line segments between two points on them are called chords. For ten points, name these shapes that have a constant radius.",
        "answer": "circles"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Lindemann proved that pi was transcendental in 1882, roughly a decade after this Swiss mathematician’s namesake number was proven transcendental by Charles Hermite. This man was patronized by Frederick the Great.",
        "answer": "Leonhard Euler"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Battle of Wuzhang Plains took place during this period and ended after the death of Zhuge Liang. A leader of this period was stunted at the Battle of Red Cliffs, which precipitated the rise of two rivals. Sima Yan established the Jin dynasty during this period by overthrowing the Cao Cao-founded Wei. The collapse of the Han dynasty led to, for ten points, what strife-filled period of Chinese history, named for the number of major combatants?",
        "answer": "Three Kingdoms period"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The tumult of the Three Kingdoms period essentially started in 184 AD with this peasant revolt, led by Zhang Jiao.",
        "answer": [
          "Yellow Turban Rebellion",
          "Yellow Scarves Rebellion"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was disguised as a drunk flight attendant to avoid suspicion on a Bristol Britannia plane. A month earlier, as this man was getting off a bus in Buenos Aires, Peter Malkin and two other agents of Mossad tackled and abducted this man. Hannah Arendt wrote about the “banality of evil” as displayed by this man at his 1961 trial for war crimes in Jerusalem. For ten points, name this man who hid in Argentina for a decade before being executed for his role in orchestrating the Holocaust.",
        "answer": "Otto Adolf Eichmann"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Eichmann’s role in the Holocaust included devising a plan to deport Jews to this island in the Southern Hemisphere.",
        "answer": "Madagascar Plan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler created an administrative system with 33 ranks and a standardized system of payment called the mansabdari system. This ruler, who was advised by the Nine Jewels, created the House of Worship for discussions between different religious leaders. The Din-i-Ilahi syncretic religion, founded by this ruler, replaced Islam as the state religion. This son of Humayun defeated the Hindu king Hemu at the Second Battle of Panipat. For ten points, name this third Mughal emperor, the grandson of Babur.",
        "answer": "Akbar the Great"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Akbar’s policies of religious toleration included a temporary end to this tax, which was levied on non-Muslims. Later Mughal rulers resumed this tax.",
        "answer": "jizya tax"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A leader of one of these organizations, Dave Beck, pled the Fifth Amendment when he was called to testify in front of the McClellan Committee. Voting procedures in these organizations are governed by the Landrum-Griffin Act. Agreements whereby people vowed not to join these organizations, or yellow dog contracts, were outlawed by the Norris-LaGuardia Act. For ten points, name these organizations that may engage in collective bargaining with management on behalf of their working members.",
        "answer": [
          "labor unions",
          "Teamsters during the first sentence"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Currently, 28 states have passed this type of law prohibiting contracts or hiring conditions that compel workers to join unions. Some opponents of this type of law note that its three-word name is misleading.",
        "answer": "right-to-work law"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One attempt to bankrupt this organization involved transferring its funds into the Alliance of Trade Unions, or OPZZ. After putting forth the 21 demands of the Inter-Enterprise committee, this organization argued for reforms with Wojciech Jaruzelski [voy-check yah-roo-zel-ski]. Shortly after a popular manager, Anna Walentynowicz, was fired, this organization went on strike at the Lenin Shipyard in Gdansk. Lech Walesa [lek vah-wen-sah] led, for ten points, what influential Polish labor union and political movement?",
        "answer": "Solidarity or Solidarnosc"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This aforementioned set of negotiations between Solidarity and the Polish government led to a namesake agreement legalizing trade unions and creating a Senate, which Solidarity promptly dominated after elections in June 1989.",
        "answer": "Round Table Talks or Round Table Negotiation, Agreement, etc."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s followers swore the Pledge of the Tree while one of his ambassadors was being held hostage. This commander’s troops fended off a far larger besieging army in the Battle of the Trench. This man defeated a contingent representing the Quraysh merchants at the Battle of Badr, after which he consolidated his base of power in Medina. Mecca was conquered by, for ten points, what leader who performed the Hijra migration and founded Islam?",
        "answer": "Muhammad"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man, who served as a guard during the Battle of the Trench and the Battle of Badr, is nicknamed “The Truthful” and became the first Caliph after Muhammad’s death.",
        "answer": "Abu Bakr as-Siddiq"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was assaulted by Frankie Gallucio while working at the Harvard Inn under his mentor Frankie Yale. The “Untouchables” were created by Eliot Ness to counter this man, who was the first criminal to be labeled “Public Enemy Number One.” An attack that was probably ordered by this man targeted Bugs Moran and his Northside Gang. Tax evasion was the ultimate downfall of, for ten points, what Chicago gangster known as “Scarface?”",
        "answer": "Alphonse “Al” Gabriel Capone"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The attack on Bugs Moran’s Northside Gang took place on this holiday in 1929.",
        "answer": "Saint Valentine’s Day Massacre"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The masses of these entities are governed by the whole number rule as described by Francis Aston, whose cousin Margaret Todd suggested a name for these entities from the Greek for “at the same place.” One of the 15 of these entities for carbon is used in radioactive dating, has a half-life of 5,700 years, and has eight neutrons instead of the more stable six-neutron form. For ten points, give this term for variants of the same element that have different atomic masses.",
        "answer": "isotopes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This element is most commonly found with an atomic mass of 238, but its 235 isotope is fissile and thus usable in nuclear weapons like Little Boy.",
        "answer": "uranium"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This language’s 7th century Kufic style of calligraphy is based on straight lines and right angles. Like other languages in its family, including Hebrew, this language builds words around three-consonant roots. The “Modern Standard” variety of this language is commonly used in literature and the news, despite the wide variance in dialects. This language’s writing system lends its name to the term abjad, for an alphabet without vowels. For ten points, name this primary language spoken in Morocco, Egypt, and Qatar.",
        "answer": "Arabic"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Arabic and Hebrew belong to this five-millennia-old language family, which also includes Amharic, Syriac, and Maltese.",
        "answer": "Semitic languages"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This group formed after the passing of the Adjusted Compensation Act and had the support of Smedley Butler. Walter Waters led this group, whose members camped on the Anacostia Flats after they were forced to wait until 1945 to redeem certificates for cash. Douglas MacArthur led federal troops to break up, for ten points, what group of disgruntled World War I veterans who marched on Washington D.C. in 1932?",
        "answer": "Bonus Army"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The day after the Bonus Army was dispersed, marcher Joe Angelo met with this US general, whose life Angelo had saved during World War I. This man, nicknamed “Old Blood and Guts,” refused to change his mind and help the marchers.",
        "answer": "George S. Patton"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Mu’tazila school disagrees that this work is “uncreated” and thus co-eternal with God. This work, which was standardized around 650 AD by Uthman ibn Affan, was first shared in a cave where Jibreel ordered a certain person to “recite!” People who memorize the entirety of this text are called Hafiz. For ten points, name this scripture divided into 114 surahs and revealed to the prophet Muhammad, the holy book of Islam.",
        "answer": "The Qur’an or Koran"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The second and longest surah of the Quran is named for this animal. A golden statue of a young one of these animals was created by the Israelites while Moses was on Mount Sinai in Exodus, leading to their punishment.",
        "answer": "cow"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Maria Reiche’s studies of these works has led her to be nicknamed “the Lady” of them. Drone research has led historians to conclude that these works were inspired by similar ones created by the Paracas Culture. An Adler Planetarium astronomer claimed that these works were created for the purpose of pointing out “heavenly shapes.” Created roughly 2,000 years ago, these works were made by the removal of dark sand to expose lighter colored soil below. Animals like jaguars and llamas are depicted in, for ten points, what natural artworks created in ancient Peru?",
        "answer": "Nazca Lines"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A theory about the creation of the Nazca Lines involves a medieval version of this object to observe the designs. The Montgolfier brothers famously designed one of these objects.",
        "answer": "hot-air balloon"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was nearly removed in a recall election after the Sauk Prairie Star began a campaign saying he “must go.” This man attacked Margaret Chase Smith and her allies as “Snow White and the six dwarfs” after he was criticized in her Declaration of Conscience speech. This man’s notoriety came to an end during a series of hearings on the Army, where Joseph Welch asked him “have you no sense of decency?” For ten points, name this Wisconsin senator who fueled a 1950’s Red Scare.",
        "answer": "Joseph McCarthy"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1950 in West Virginia, McCarthy infamously claimed he possessed a list of 205 communists within this governmental department.",
        "answer": "State Department"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This king’s forces captured Minorca, leading to the execution of John Byng. Robert-Francois Damien’s attempt to kill this man was foiled by his thick winter clothes. This man’s minister Cardinal Fleury punished Jansenist priests, and his mistress supported Enlightenment philosophers like Voltaire. The saying “Apres moi, le deluge” or “after me, the flood” is attributed to, for ten points, what great-grandson of the Sun King, Louis XIV [14]?",
        "answer": "Louis XV"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This official mistress of Louis XV was depicted in several Francois Boucher [boo-shay] paintings, including one of her playing the harpsichord.",
        "answer": "Jeanna Antoinette Poisson, the Madame de Pompadour"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Amerigo Vespucci may have been named after a son of this man who had died in a boar hunting accident in present day Romania. That son, Emeric, was born to this man by a Bavarian princess named Gisela. The doctrine of primogeniture was used to justify this man’s succession following the death of Geza rather than that of this man’s uncle, who ruled portions of Transdanubia. This man was baptized at Esztergom [ess-ter-gohm], where he now serves as the patron saint. For ten points, name this first King of Hungary.",
        "answer": "Stephen I of Hungary or Saint Stephen"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Saint Stephen was a member of this ruling dynasty of Hungary, which died out in the early 14th century.",
        "answer": "Arpad Dynasty"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was allegedly so impressed by ally Isaac Brock that he presented the general to his troops, saying “this is a man!” The numbers of this man’s armies swelled after the New Madrid Earthquake was interpreted as a sign to join him; those alliances disintegrated with his death at the Battle of the Thames. For ten points, name this brother of “the Prophet,” a Shawnee chief who led a coalition of natives in support of England during the War of 1812.",
        "answer": "Tecumseh"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Union general and leader of a “March to the Sea” through Georgia was given the name Tecumseh by his father.",
        "answer": "William Tecumseh Sherman"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Non-dualistic philosophy is touted in this faith’s Advaita Vedanta, inspiring movements like the medieval Bhakti Movement. Governor General Hastings defeated an empire of this faith named the Maratha in the third British war against them. With the arrival of spring, members of this faith celebrate its Festival of Color, Holi. For ten points, name this religion, the majority faith of India.",
        "answer": "Hinduism"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The minority religions of India include this faith, whose adherents formed an empire in the Punjab in the early 19th century. Nanak, who lived in the early 16th century, was this religion’s founder and first guru.",
        "answer": "Sikhism"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At a battle in this state, forces under Sterling Price used bales of water soaked hemp to absorb Union artillery. In addition to the First Battle of Lexington, this state was home to the Battle of Wilson’s Creek, which gave the Confederacy control of its southwestern corner. Bloody Bill Anderson’s bushwhackers carried out the Centralia Massacre in this state, which was admitted to the Union simultaneously with Maine. For ten points, name this state, the subject of an 1820 “Compromise.”",
        "answer": "Missouri"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Among the men who carried out the Centralia Massacre under Bloody Bill Anderson was this man, whose later crimes included a botched bank robbery in Northfield, Minnesota in 1876 with his brother Frank.",
        "answer": "Jesse James"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man, who was sued by Charlotte Dupuy, hired Benjamin Latrobe to design the mansion at his Ashland estate. Domestically, this man’s negotiations resulted in California being admitted as a free state and the prohibition of slavery north of the 36-30 parallel, leading him to be known as the “Great Compromiser.” For ten points, name this Kentucky politician who formulated the Compromise of 1850 and Missouri Compromise.",
        "answer": "Henry Clay"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Henry Clay held this position during the debate over the Missouri Compromise. He left this position to become Secretary of State in the John Quincy Adams administration.",
        "answer": "Speaker of the House of Representatives"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man, who was discovered lurking in the woods by Benjamin Phipps, is discussed as an inspiration in the autobiography of Henry “Box” Brown. Jim Travis was one of the targets of an event organized by this man, who was inspired by the viewing of a solar eclipse. This man lived in Southampton County, where he was inspired by Denmark Vesey to carry out an attack that resulted in roughly 60 deaths. For ten points, name this leader of an 1831 slave rebellion.",
        "answer": "Nat Turner"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Nat Turner’s slave revolt took place in this state’s Southampton County. Turner was captured in this state’s portion of the Great Dismal Swamp.",
        "answer": "Virginia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this king’s reign, a vernacular service known as the Exhortation and Litany was written. Martin Luther’s attack on indulgences prompted this man to write Defense of the Seven Sacraments. This king was given the title of “Defender of the Faith” by Pope Leo X, but a disagreement with Clement VII over whether this king’s marriage could be annulled led him to split with the Catholic Church. For ten points, name this Tudor King who created the Church of England after splitting with the first of his six wives.",
        "answer": "Henry VIII"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Exhortation and Litany was written by Thomas Cranmer, who held this position during Henry VIII’s rule.",
        "answer": "Archbishop of Canterbury"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Nine stages of this location were made out of the tail of Cipactli [see-pock-t’lee], according to stories recorded in the Florentine Codex. An alternative to this location was ruled by Tlaloc [t’lal-ok] and populated by those who had been struck by lightning or drowned; another alternative location was the destination of human sacrifices. Mictlan is the name of, for ten points, what location in Aztec myth through which Xolotl [sho-lot’ll] guided souls?",
        "answer": [
          "Aztec underworld",
          "Mictlan before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Florentine Codex was compiled by Bernardino de Sahagun, a friar from this order that is named for a 13th century saint from Assisi.",
        "answer": [
          "Franciscans",
          "Saint Francis of Assisi"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This story’s postscript warns that “he that runs races with goblin troopers will have rough riding of it.” The tendency of married men to linger about the taverns in this story’s setting give it the nickname Tarry Town. This story’s protagonist rides the horse Gunpowder and competes with the character Brom Bones for the affection of Katrina Van Tassel. For ten points, name this story from The Sketch Book of Geoffrey Crayon featuring a cursed Hessian soldier and the schoolmaster Ichabod Crane, written by Washington Irving.",
        "answer": "The Legend of Sleepy Hollow"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The ghost of this spy supposedly haunts a tree in “The Legend of Sleepy Hollow” near where Ichabod Crane encounters the Headless Horseman. This spy was hanged on October 2, 1780, after having been caught near Tarrytown with six pages of incriminating evidence in his boot.",
        "answer": "John Andr´e"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler’s death was kept secret by Sokollu Mehmed Pasha to maintain troop morale during the siege of Szigetvar. This ruler made peace with Shah Tahmasp of the Safavid Empire in the Peace of Amasya and signed another treaty with Francis I to form an “Unholy Alliance” to check the power of the Habsburgs. Though this man could not conquer Vienna, he was victorious at a 1526 battle in Hungary. For ten points, name the longest reigning Ottoman sultan.",
        "answer": [
          "Suleiman I",
          "Suleiman the Magnificent"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Suleiman won this 1526 battle over Louis II, splitting Hungary between Ottoman and Habsburg rule.",
        "answer": "Battle of Mohacs , but be lenient"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Peter the Patrician negotiated the end of the Lazic War for this ruler, who had also ended a war with Khosrau I in the Perpetual Peace. The Four Doctors of Bologna revived this man’s law code, the Corpus Juris Civilis. A work by Procopius describes Hypatius’s attempt to rally the Blues and Greens to overthrow this husband of Theodora. The general Belisarius quelled the Nika Revolts for, for ten points, what Byzantine emperor who constructed the Hagia Sophia?",
        "answer": "Justinian I or Justinian the Great"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Procopius described Justinian as possessed by a demon in this highly critical unpublished work, which was discovered in the Vatican in the 17th century.",
        "answer": [
          "Secret History",
          "Historia Arcana",
          "Anekdota"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This group conspired with Amalric of Tyre to overthrow Henry II of Cyprus. This group was allowed to pay no taxes and travel freely across borders by Pope Innocent II’s papal bull Omne Datum Optimum, which may have been prompted by support from this group’s patron, Bernard of Clairvaux. This group relieved Baldwin IV’s forces at Montgisard. Members of this group were arrested for heresy by Philip IV, after which many joined the Knights Hospitaller. For ten points, name this chivalric order active in the crusades.",
        "answer": "Knights Templar"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Knights Templar were officially dissolved by this Pope, whose refusal to move to Rome ushered in the Avignon Papacy.",
        "answer": "Clement V"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this period, the May Report advocated for expenditure cuts, and the Left Book Club produced monthly warnings during this period. Hunger marches in this era included one by ship workers from Jarrow. Oswald Mosely advocated for greater pensions and control over banks in this period before founding his own Fascist Party. After a mutiny, the gold standard was abandoned by England during this period. For ten points, name this period of economic decline that began after a crash on Wall Street.",
        "answer": "Great Depression"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Before the Depression, a welfare state was created by this party in the UK, whose leaders included H. H. Asquith. This party has been replaced by the Labour Party as the primary rival of the Conservatives.",
        "answer": "Liberal Party"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Judge John G. Davies criticized this man, who invested in Straight Alta-Pazz Records. A George Holliday film shows this man being attacked while with Bryant Allen and Freddie Helms, after which this man wrote The Riot Within. Tim and Melanie Singer first encountered this man on the highway, and Daryl Gates said excessive force was used on this man. This man was quoted saying, \"Can we all just get along?\" For ten points, name this man who was beaten by the LAPD in 1991 causing citywide riots.",
        "answer": "Rodney King"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Baptist minister delivered Rodney King's eulogy, hosts the radio show Keepin' It Real, and founded the civil rights organization, National Action Network.",
        "answer": "Al Sharpton"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This war included the Downes and Porter Expedition, as well as the Battle at Typee Valley. During this war, the navy attacked Polynesians at Nuku Hiva after Madisonville was founded. This war included the battle of Valparaiso in which David Porter captured the USS Essex. Besides its Pacific theatre, another campaign in this war included fighting at Lake Borgne and the Villeré Plantation, during which Edward Pakenham engaged Andrew Jackson at New Orleans. For ten points, name this war which Fort McHenry's flag survived.",
        "answer": "War of 1812"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "David Porter's adopted son was this Union admiral who captured Mobile Bay during the Civil War.",
        "answer": "David Farragut"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of the few survivors of this battle were Susanna Dickinson and a slave named Joe, both of whom were spared by an enemy commander. That commander at this battle would later be defeated at the Battle of San Jacinto [[hah- SEEN-toe]]. The location of this battle was depicted on a stamp in 1856 to celebrate the anniversary of Texan statehood. A fortified mission was attacked in, for ten points, what battle of the Texan War of Independence that would go on to become a famous battle cry?",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of the Alamo",
          "\"Remember the Alamo\""
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Kentucky-born colonel was sent to reinforce the mission prior to the Battle of the Alamo. A large type of hunting knife bears this man's name.",
        "answer": [
          "James Bowie ]",
          "Bowie Knife"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Though officially called the Revolutionary Nuns, a \"Guard\" nicknamed for this legendary culture served under Muammar Gaddafi of Libya. Strabo [[STRAY-boh]] claimed that these people lived along the Thermodon [[THER-moh-don]] River though they had retreated beyond the realm of the Gargareans [[gar-GAR-ee-ans]] with whom these people reproduced children. Legendarily led by Penthesilea [[pen-theh-sih-LAY-uh]] during the Attic War, for ten points, what was this culture of warrior women who may have lived in Scythia [[SIH-thee-ah]]?",
        "answer": [
          "Amazons",
          "Amazonian Guard"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Virgil modelled the warrior Camilla [[kah-MIH-lah]] on the Amazons in this epic poem about a Trojan prince who travels to Italy and becomes the ancestor of the Romans.",
        "answer": [
          "Aeneid ]",
          "The Aeneid",
          "Aenē ̆is"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One account of this conflict ends at the Battle of Ascalon, where Godfrey of Bouillon [[boo-YOHN]] drove off the army of the Fatimids. Seljuk leader Kilij [[kee-LEEJ]] Arslan's lightly armored horse archers were defeated in this conflict by a combined Italo-Norman force at Dorylaeum [[DOR-ee-LAY-uhm]]. A Byzantine request for aid led to, for ten points, what 11th century war to recapture of the Holy Land from Muslim control?",
        "answer": [
          "First Crusade",
          "Princes' Crusade"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The First Crusade was initiated by this Frenchman who reigned as Pope from 1088 to 1099. He is best known for possibly being the source of the rallying cry \"Deus Vult!\" or \"God wills it!\"",
        "answer": [
          "Pope Urban II",
          "Odo of Châtillon",
          "Otho de Lagery"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man failed to pay a 500 lira bet with Duke Caetani [[cah-eh-TAH-nee]] after losing a sporting event against butteri Augusto Imperiali while on tour in Italy. This man and an organization named for him were denied entry into the 1893 World's Fair, so he set up his show directly outside the fairgrounds. This man's show included reenactments of bison hunts, the Battle of Little Bighorn, and the charge up San Juan Hill. For ten points, name this figure, the owner of a \"Wild West\" show which included figures like Sitting Bull and Annie Oakley.",
        "answer": [
          "Buffalo Bill",
          "William Frederick Cody"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Buffalo Bill was a member of what secretive fraternal order which derived its rules from medieval guild laws? Its members included George Washington and Benjamin Franklin.",
        "answer": [
          "Freemasons",
          "Masons",
          "or Freemasonry"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This oratorio was based on a text compiled from the Coverdale Psalter and King James Bible by Charles Jennens. Part one of this oratorio depicts the salvation of Isaiah, and that scene in this work is punctuated by And the Glory of the Lord. A popular legend states that George II began the tradition of standing during this piece's Hallelujah Chorus. For ten points, name this oratorio often performed at Christmas, written by George Frideric Handel.",
        "answer": "Messiah"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Although he often performed in London, Handel's Messiah debuted on this island, which had been controlled by the English since 1603.",
        "answer": "Ireland or Eire"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this project, General Leslie Groves undertook a propaganda campaign to prevent \"loose talk\" by its participants. Despite his acts of treason, Klaus Fuchs [[FYOOKS]] was a key component on this project's development but later served nine years in prison for his actions. Because of his study and understanding of fast neutrons, Robert Oppenheimer was a prime member of this project. For ten points, name this top-secret U.S. project which developed the atomic bomb.",
        "answer": [
          "Manhattan Project",
          "Development of Substitute Materials"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which New Mexico city was home to much of the Manhattan Project and today houses a museum dedicated to the project?",
        "answer": "Los Alamos"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "THE PROTESTANT REFORMATION",
      "prompt": "During the Protestant Reformation, what...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Man nailed Ninety-Five theses to a church door?",
          "answer": "Martin Luther"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tudor king of England created the Church of England?",
          "answer": "Henry VIII"
        },
        {
          "question": "French theologian wrote Institutes of the Christian Religion?",
          "answer": "John Calvin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Author of Utopia was executed?",
          "answer": "Sir Thomas More"
        },
        {
          "question": "Church council began the Counter-Reformation?",
          "answer": "Council of Trent"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty established the principle of “cuius region, eius religio”?",
          "answer": "Peace of Augsburg"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Henry VIII",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "total number of wives he had.",
          "answer": "6"
        },
        {
          "question": "first woman he married.",
          "answer": "Catherine of Aragon"
        },
        {
          "question": "second woman he married, who bore him Elizabeth I?",
          "answer": "Anne Boleyn"
        },
        {
          "question": "adviser and author of Utopia who was executed for treason.",
          "answer": "Sir Thomas More"
        },
        {
          "question": "title bestowed upon him by Pope Leo X after writing Defense of the Seven Sacraments",
          "answer": "Defender of the Faith or Fidei defensor"
        },
        {
          "question": "church he founded after his excommunication by the Pope.",
          "answer": "Church of England or Anglican Church"
        },
        {
          "question": "act passed by Parliament that declared him the head of that Church?",
          "answer": "Act of Supremacy"
        },
        {
          "question": "field where Henry VIII met Francis I of France over three weeks in summer 1520.",
          "answer": "Field of the Cloth of Gold"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Wild West",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Female sharpshooter and partner of Frank Butler, known as “Little Sure Shot.”",
          "answer": "Annie Oakley"
        },
        {
          "question": "Owner of the traveling Wild West Show that employed that sharpshooter, as well as Sitting Bull.",
          "answer": [
            "William Frederick Cody",
            "Buffalo Bill Cody"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Card game played by Wild Bill Hickok when he was shot dead, holding two pair.",
          "answer": [
            "five-card stud poker",
            "five card stud"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Quick mail service that used mounted riders and survived less than two years until the telegraph’s invention.",
          "answer": "Pony Express"
        },
        {
          "question": "1862 act that granted 160 acres of land to citizens willing to work and improve the land for five years.",
          "answer": [
            "Homestead Act or Bill",
            "Law"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "State where the Gunfight at the OK Corral took place in Tombstone.",
          "answer": "Arizona"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Coward” who shot and killed Jesse James in April 1882.",
          "answer": "Robert Ford"
        },
        {
          "question": "Confederate leader whose guerrilla “Raiders,” including Jesse James, raided Lawrence, Kansas in August 1863.",
          "answer": [
            "William Quantrill",
            "Quantrill’s Raiders"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Henry VIII",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Royal English house to which Henry belonged.",
          "answer": "House of Tudor"
        },
        {
          "question": "Number of women Henry married during his life.",
          "answer": "six"
        },
        {
          "question": "First wife of Henry VIII, the daughter of Ferdinand and Isabella.",
          "answer": "Catherine of Aragon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Church that Henry founded after the pope would not grant him an annulment to that wife.",
          "answer": "Anglican Church or Church of England"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wife who gave birth to Henry’s son Edward VI.",
          "answer": "Jane Seymour"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last woman to marry Henry VIII.",
          "answer": "Catherine Parr"
        },
        {
          "question": "1536 uprising led by Robert Aske in protest of Henry VIII’s anti-Catholic policies.",
          "answer": "Pilgrimage of Grace"
        },
        {
          "question": "War fought during Henry’s reign with the aim of securing his son’s marriage to Mary, Queen of Scots.",
          "answer": "War of the Rough Wooing"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Hamas",
      "prompt": "Name the…...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Holy Middle Eastern city where the predecessor of Hamas set up branches.",
          "answer": "Jerusalem"
        },
        {
          "question": "Islamic sect Hamas supports, as contrasted with Shia Islam.",
          "answer": "Sunni Islam"
        },
        {
          "question": "Strip of land bordering Egypt and Israel which Hamas governs.",
          "answer": "Gaza Strip"
        },
        {
          "question": "Weapons Hamas uses, defended from by Israel’s Iron Dome.",
          "answer": [
            "Rockets",
            "\"artillery shells,\" \"missiles,\" and other similar descriptive answers"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Egyptian organization from which Hamas stems, upon which Nasser cracked down.",
          "answer": "Muslim Brotherhood or Society of the Muslim Brothers"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hamas was formed after the first of these Palestinian uprisings against Israel that often involved civilians throwing projectiles.",
          "answer": "Intifada"
        },
        {
          "question": "Military wing of Hamas, as contrasted with the Dawah.",
          "answer": [
            "Izz ad-Din al-Qassam Brigades",
            "EQB"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1994 Massacre of Muslims by Baruch Goldstein, which prompted Hamas to start targeting civilians.",
          "answer": [
            "Cave of the Patriarchs Massacre or Ibrahimi Mosque Massacre",
            "or Hebron Massacre 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 2"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An anonymous proposal suggested finding this value by having wounded dogs bark at regular intervals. After the Scilly Islands disaster in 1707, a prize was created for the person who could create a (20 pts)",
        "method for finding this value. Some of that prize money was awarded to John Harrison, whose marine (10 pts)",
        "chronometer gave sailors an accurate time that could be used to calculate it. For 10 points, name this geographic coordinate that identifies East- West position, as opposed to latitude."
      ],
      "answer": "longitude"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man attempted to use Gamma Draconis to measure the distance to a star using parallax, but was unable to obtain accurate measurements. This man's observations of a cork plant are collected in his (20 pts)",
        "Micrographia. This longtime leader of the Royal Society in the late seventeenth century also proposed a (10 pts)",
        "\"restoring force\" proportional to distance. For 10 points, name this English polymath who lends his name to a law for the action of springs."
      ],
      "answer": "Robert Hooke"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The founder of this group was arrested alongside Victor Tirado, after which he wrote From Prison, I Accuse the Dictatorship. Jaime Wheelock Roman led the “Proletarian Tendency” subgroup of this party. This group overthrow Anastasio (20 pts)",
        "Somoza Debayle, after which John Poindexter and Oliver North funneled money to groups (10 pts)",
        "opposing this party. For 10 points, name this Nicaraguan political party opposed by the Contras."
      ],
      "answer": "Sandinista National Liberation Front"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This group was the subject of a synod convened by William Courtenay that was interrupted by an earthquake. Thomas Arundel persecuted this group. A member of this group, John Oldcastle, led a rebellion against Henry V. John of (20 pts)",
        "Gaunt protected the founder of this group. The name of this group may derive from a (10 pts)",
        "Dutch word for \"mumbler.\" For 10 points, name this proto-Reformation religious movement led by John Wycliffe."
      ],
      "answer": "Lollards"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This material was \"crimped and extruded\" to deal with traction problems. This material was originally called ChemGrass when it was invented by Donald Elbert for Monsanto in the early 1960s. This material was susceptible to intentionally bounced (20 pts)",
        "underthrows, perfected by Dave Concepcion. This material solved the problem of getting enough light to the inside of a (10 pts)",
        "Houston baseball stadium. For 10 points, name this pioneering artificial grass substitute."
      ],
      "answer": "Astroturf"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After this war, the Titulus Regius was repealed. During this war, a king negotiated the Treaty of Piquniny with “the Universal Spider,” Louis XI. A leader of one of this war’s sides married Elizabeth (20 pts)",
        "Woodville, thus alienating his ally Warwick the Kingmaker. This war ended after (10 pts)",
        "Richard III was defeated at the Battle of Bosworth Field. For 10 points, name this conflict between the houses of Lancaster and York, which were represented by red and white flowers."
      ],
      "answer": "War of the Roses"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In response to this event, a system was announced in which alternate-day accessibility was determined by the last digit of a car's license plate. This event, a classic example of an economic (20 pts)",
        "\"supply shock,\" was a response to perceived U.S. support of Israel in the Yom Kippur War. This event was engineered by (10 pts)",
        "OPEC and devastated the economy under Richard Nixon. For 10 points, identify this 1973 event which caused long lines at gas stations."
      ],
      "answer": "OPEC oil embargo"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Judica-Cordiglia recordings purportedly captured transmissions from the \"lost\" group of these people, whose existence or death is believed to have been suppressed. One of these people died in a 1968 (20 pts)",
        "fighter jet crash, seven years after using the Vostok. These people included (10 pts)",
        "Valentina Tereshkova and Yuri Gagarin. For 10 points, identify these people who included the first-ever man in space, and were the stars of the Soviet space program."
      ],
      "answer": "cosmonauts"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The founder of this religion is depicted reacting to sweetness in the painting The Vinegar\nTasters. Mystics within this religion formed the Five Pecks of Rice Society, which formed a\nbreakaway state that followed the (20 pts) ",
        "\"Celestial Master.\" This religion was believed to be\nfounded by a 900-year-old man who was forced to write down The Book of the (10 pts) ",
        "Way\nbefore leaving for the West. For 10 points, name this traditional, non-Confucian religion of\nChina."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Daoism",
        "Taoism"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A news photographer captured an assault on Richard Frankensteen, a leader of this\nunion, by surrendering fake photo plates. This union, now led by Dennis Williams,\nrepresents many (20 pts) ",
        "graduate students. This union, which operated a dedicated radio\nstation, was involved in the \"Battle of the (10 pts) ",
        "Overpass\" during its leadership by Walter\nReuther. The 1937 Flint sit-down strike gave it official recognition. For 10 points, name this\nunion of car industry employees."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "UAW",
        "United Automobile Workers",
        "United Auto Workers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These things were first discovered using Charles Chamberlain's porcelain filters. By\n1910, Peyton Rous demonstrated their role in cancers. In 1892, Dmitri Ivanovsky\ndemonstrated that these things caused the (20 pts) ",
        "tobacco mosaic disease. Walter Reed found\nthe first large-scale human consequence of these things, when he showed that one of them\ncauses (*) yellow fever. (10 pts) ",
        "For 10 points, name this quasi-living genetic information vector that is\nnot a bacteria."
      ],
      "answer": "virus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Like Pope Pius IX, this leader was presented with a Golden Telephone by the ITT Corporation, and this man imprisoned the leaders of the Conspiracy of the Pure. This man came to power after cancelling an election in which he was opposed by the Orthodox Party and the Authentic Party. This man overthrew (20 pts)",
        "Gerardo Machado as leader of the Sargents’ Revolt, and was overthrown by the (10 pts)",
        "July 26th movement. For 10 points, name this dictator of Cuba overthrown by Fidel Castro."
      ],
      "answer": "Fulgencio Batista y Zaldívar"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This family abolished the post of Gonfaloniere of Justice. An early member of this family helped suppress the revolt of wool-carders called Ciompi. Two members of this family were attacked at High Mass during the (20 pts)",
        "Pazzi Conspiracy. A member of this family, Piero the Unfortunate, lost power to a friar who held the (10 pts)",
        "\"bonfire of the vanities,\" Domenico Savonarola. For 10 points, name this family headed by Cosimo and Lorenzo, which ruled Florence."
      ],
      "answer": "House of Medici"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This group was tricked into releasing 15 hostages in Operation Jaque, and its leader currently has the alias Timochenko. Three IRA members, James Monaghan, Martin McCauley, and Niall Connolly, were accused of teaching this group (20 pts)",
        "bomb-making. This group was originally founded after an attack on the Marquetalia Republic, which was founded after La (10 pts)",
        "Violencia. For 10 points, name this terrorist group and cocaine smuggling outfit based in Colombia."
      ],
      "answer": "FARC"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Security guard Frank Wills uncovered the central incident in this event, which led to the second use of 96-point font in New York Times history, after the Moon landings. It was masterminded by G. Gordon (20 pts)",
        "Liddy and E. Howard Hunt. This event was investigated by (10 pts)",
        "Washington Post reporters Carl Bernstein and Bob Woodward, who received tips from an informant known as “Deep Throat.” The burglary of the DNC headquarters and ensuing coverup were the subject of, for ten points, what scandal that resulted in the resignation of Richard Nixon."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Watergate scandal",
        "descriptions of Nixon’s resignation before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Juana Navarro Alsbury was brought to this location by her cousin and may have tried to surrender it. Courier James Allen is the last confirmed man to have (20 pts)",
        "left this building, in which Susanna Dickinson hid in a church sacristy. James (10 pts)",
        "Bowie and Davy Crockett died at, for ten points, what San Antonio mission, the site of an 1836 battle where every Texan soldier was killed by Santa Anna’s army?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of the Alamo"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Michael O’Rahilly was shot by a machine gun on Moore Street during this event, and it was described in a W.B. Yeats poem as “a terrible beauty is born”. James (20 pts)",
        "Connolly lead a Citizen Army during this event, where its instigators had their headquarters at the General Post Office. The aftermath of this event led to the (10 pts)",
        "executions of Patrick Pearse and Roger Casement and saw the rise of the Sinn Fein Party. For ten points, name this 1916 uprising in Ireland named after a Christian holiday."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Easter Rising",
        "Easter Rebellion"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) John Dickinson, the author of Letters from a Pennsylvania Farmer, refused to sign this document. Charles Thomson presided over the meeting that produced this document, and sent its final, handwritten copy to John Dunlap for (20 pts)",
        "printing. Richard Henry Lee introduced the resolution creating this document, and Roger Sherman and Benjamin (10 pts)",
        "Franklin served on the Committee of Five that edited this text. For ten points, name this document whose Preamble asserts that “We hold these truths to be self-evident, that all men are created equal,” written by Thomas Jefferson."
      ],
      "answer": "Declaration of Independence"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) William Cosby was the target of one man who made his fortune through the sale of these entities. An account titled “Heed Their Rising Voices” was published by one organization that created these entities and led to a (20 pts)",
        "lawsuit that established the standard of “actual malice” with regards to libel. John (10 pts)",
        "Peter Zenger, a printer of these documents, was acquitted in a case that established truth as a defense against libel. For ten points, name these periodicals, the subject of the court case New York Times v. Sullivan."
      ],
      "answer": "newspapers"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader allowed for the publishing of Alexander Solzhenitsyn’s One Day in the Life of Ivan Denisovich and he attempted to increase agricultural production by starting the (20 pts)",
        "Virgin Lands Campaign. This leader reportedly banged his shoe on a table during a U.N. Conference and 4 years earlier had told Western diplomats “we will (10 pts)",
        "bury you!” He complained about his predecessor’s personality cult in the “Secret Speech” and was replaced in his highest position by Leonid Brezhnev. For ten points, name this Soviet leader during the Cuban Missile Crisis."
      ],
      "answer": "Nikita Khrushchev"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Members of this religion prompted native Americans to attack members of the Baker- Fancher settlers in the (20 pts)",
        "Mountain Meadows Massacre. This religion’s founder wished to create a utopian “Zion” after being forced by Lilburn Boggs’s Extermination Order to migrate to (10 pts)",
        "Nauvoo, Illinois. For ten points, name this religion founded by Joseph Smith, whose members make up the majority of the population in Utah."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Mormonism",
        "Mormons",
        "Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints",
        "LDS"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This successor of Johnny Torrio claimed that a war wound, rather than Frank Gallucio’s knife, inspired his nickname. Despite ordering the (20 pts)",
        "killings of dozens of men, probably including the seven killed in the St. Valentine’s Day Massacre, he was only convicted of (10 pts)",
        "tax evasion. For ten points, name this man, nicknamed “Scarface,” who led the Chicago mob during Prohibition."
      ],
      "answer": "Alphonse Gabriel “Al” Capone"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One philosophical split in this movement pitted Lysander Spooner’s arguments against those of Wendell Phillips’ “disunionists.” Bates College and Oberlin College were founded in support of this movement, and (20 pts)",
        "Elijah Lovejoy was killed by a mob in Illinois for supporting it. Newspapers devoted to this cause included (10 pts)",
        "The North Star and The Liberator, published by William Lloyd Garrison. For ten points, name this movement led by Frederick Douglass, whose goal was to end slavery."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "abolitionism or abolition of slavery",
        "ending slavery",
        "equivalents before “slavery”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Sociologist George Ritzer used this company as a metaphor for cultural homogenization. Thomas Friedman has claimed that no two countries where this company does business have ever gone to war with each other. Since 1986, the price of this corporation’s signature product has been used in an (20 pts)",
        "“index” measuring purchasing power by The Economist. Stella Liebeck’s lawsuit against this corporation was explored in the documentary (10 pts)",
        "Hot Coffee. For ten points, name this fast food restaurant chain that sells the Big Mac."
      ],
      "answer": "McDonald’s"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This speech was delivered shortly after an incendiary speech by “Pitchfork Ben” Tillman failed to sway the audience. This speech notes “It is the issue of 1776 over again” in describing the need for (20 pts)",
        "international agreement on its central issue, which was supported by the Bland-Allison Act. This speech, given in Chicago at the (10 pts)",
        "Democratic National Convention, uses the Biblical image of a crown of thorns in its climax. For ten points, name this 1896 William Jennings Bryan speech which advocated for free silver and proclaimed “you shall not crucify mankind” upon the title structure."
      ],
      "answer": "Cross of Gold speech"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This politician’s “Syracuse speech” defended the Fugitive Slave Law in the Compromise of 1850, earning him ire from Horace Mann. His “Plea for Harmony and Peace” speech was defended by John F. Kennedy in Profiles in Courage. The (20 pts)",
        "Know-Nothing Party put this man’s name on the ballot in the 1852 election. This senator, who declared “Liberty and Union, (10 pts)",
        "now and forever, one and inseparable,” signed a treaty setting Maine’s border with Baron Ashburton. For ten points, name this Massachusetts orator who formed the Great Triumvirate with Calhoun and Clay."
      ],
      "answer": "Daniel Webster"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man climbed the “Mount of the Hermit” while in Quanzhou after receiving support from the Delhi sultan Muhammad bin Tughluq. This ambassador to the Yuan Dynasty fought off Alfonso XI at Gibraltar in a defense of his (20 pts)",
        "native Morocco and was commanded by Abu Inan Faris to allow (10 pts)",
        "Ibn Juzayy to document his experiences. For ten points, name this author of the Rihla, an account of his travels through the medieval Muslim world."
      ],
      "answer": "Muhammad Ibn Battuta"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The diplomats that negotiated this treaty included Lords Sumner and Cunliffe, the “Heavenly Twins.” This treaty included global recognition of the International Opium Convention and the establishment of the Free City of (20 pts)",
        "Danzig. The issue of Vietnamese indepenence was ignored during its negotiations, despite the pleas of then-student Ho Chi Minh. Article 231 of this treaty, known as the War (10 pts)",
        "Guilt clause, required harsh reparations that were accurately predicted to lead to another war. For ten points, name this treaty, signed in France in 1919, that ended World War I."
      ],
      "answer": "Treaty of Versailles"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Proper acquisition and transfer are meaningful ways of establishing rights according to this concept in Robert Nozick’s Anarchy, State, and Utopia. The idea that inequalities must be rearranged to benefit the least well off is discussed by (20 pts)",
        "John Rawls in a work about this concept. The non-comparative and comparative versions of this concept are often discussed in (10 pts)",
        "criminal law. For ten points, name this philosophical concept often represented by a blindfolded woman holding a set of scales in courtroom sculptures."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "justice",
        "A Theory of Justice"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man issued the Decree on Peace, which called for no indemnities or annexations, and passed land reform with the Decree on Land. This man condemned the government in his (20 pts)",
        "April Theses and began a series of economic reforms called the New Economic Policy. Alexander Kerensky’s government was overthrown in the (10 pts)",
        "October Revolution by this man’s forces, who defeated the White Army in the resulting civil war. For ten points, name this leader of the Bolsheviks and founder of the Soviet Union."
      ],
      "answer": "Vladimir Ilyich Lenin or Vladimir Ilyich Ulyanov"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One person who held this title reduced his army to the size of three hundred men and routed the Midianites using trumpets and clay jars. Another of these leaders repeatedly defeated the Philistines, but lost his (20 pts)",
        "uncut hair and committed suicide by toppling the temple of Dagon. (10 pts)",
        "Deborah is the only female holder of this title named in the Bible. Gideon and Samson were among, for ten points, what Israelite rulers whose history is recounted in the seventh book of the Bible?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Biblical judges",
        "Judges of Israel, Old Testament judges, and other elaborations that use the word judge",
        "shofet",
        "shoftim"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was the subject of the Rettig Report, commissioned by his successor, Patricio Aylwin. This man formed Codelco by consolidating his country’s copper mining industry, and he oversaw a period of economic revival due to the reforms of the (20 pts)",
        "Chicago Boys. This man initiated an effort to execute political prisoners known as the Caravan of Death and took part in a (10 pts)",
        "CIA-sponsored effort to support right-wing dictatorships called Operation Condor. For ten points, name this ruler of Chile who, in 1973, overthrew Salvador Allende [ah-yen-day]."
      ],
      "answer": "Augusto Pinochet"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of these pieces was premiered with satirical lyrics in the wake of a defeat in the Seven Weeks War. Maurice Ravel imitated Schubert with his “noble” and “sentimental” works of this type. (20 pts)",
        "Chopin wrote a “grande” “brilliante” piece of this type, as well as one inspired by the sight of a dog chasing its own tail, nicknamed (10 pts)",
        "“Minute.” “The Beautiful Blue Danube” is, for ten points, what type of Austrian-born dance in three-four time, often composed by its “king” Johann Strauss II?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "waltz",
        "elaborations using any of the adjectives and titles in quotemarks above"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man raised a levy from the surrounding counties at Egbert’s Stone in order to win the Battle of Ethandun. Much of the information about this man comes from (20 pts)",
        "Bishop Asser. He created a series of fortified positions known as burhs that were required to provide a form of taxes called hides. His defeat of Guthrum allowed him to establish a region known as the Danelaw. Christian principles were added to (10 pts)",
        "Saxon law codes to create the Doom Book during the reign of, for ten points, what King of Wessex, a “Great” Anglo-Saxon king?"
      ],
      "answer": "Alfred the Great or Alfred I of Wessex"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader defeated his rival Zwide [zwee-day] at the Battles of Mhlatuze [m’lah-too-zay] River and Gqokli Hill. Henry Francis Fynn was given special access to Natal after treating this man. This ruler’s downfall at the hands of his half-brother (20 pts)",
        "Dingane [din-gah-nay] was assured after he caused a famine in the wake of his mother Nandi’s death. This man’s military accomplishments included the implementation of the (10 pts)",
        "iklwa spears and “buffalo horn” formation. For ten points, name this founder of the Zulu kingdom."
      ],
      "answer": "Shaka Zulu or Shaka kaSenzangakhona"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler sought to gain prestige by fighting the War of Devolution against the Triple Alliance. In order to fund his wars against the League of Augsburg and the (20 pts)",
        "Grand Alliance, this monarch employed Jean-Baptiste Colbert to manage his kingdom’s finances. A civil war called the Fronde helped this man expand his power into an absolute monarchy. This man brought much of his nobility to the (10 pts)",
        "palace of Versailles [vair-sigh]. For ten points, name this Sun King who ruled France for over seventy years."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Louis XIV",
        "the Sun King until mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One ruler of this dynasty enlisted the help of the Sea Beggars to capture Brielle but was later assassinated by the Catholic extremist Balthasar Gerard. The Duke of Alba established the Council of Blood to quash a revolt by a (20 pts)",
        "“silent” ruler of this dynasty during the Eighty Years War. A ruler of this dynasty overthrew James I to become king of (10 pts)",
        "England during the Glorious Revolution. William III hailed from, for ten points, what colorfully named royal house of the Netherlands?"
      ],
      "answer": "House of Orange"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The breakdown of this substance was the subject of the 1987 Montreal Protocol. A 1974 paper by Molina and Rowland explains how this compound could be catalytically broken down by high frequency (20 pts)",
        "UV radiation. Each spring, a photochemical reaction depletes this compound in the troposphere over the Earth’s (10 pts)",
        "poles. Trichloroethane and other CFCs create “holes” in the atmospheric layer of, for ten points, what compound, consisting of three oxygen atoms, which protects Earth from the Sun’s radiation?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "ozone",
        "O before “oxygen” is read 3"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The victory at this battle inspired a song that began “What’s the cause of this commotion, motion, motion...” and notes “Van is a used up man.” The winning side in this battle was reinforced by the Yellow Jacket militia, and the losing commander later blamed the (20 pts)",
        "Winnebagos for attacking too early. Joseph Daviess was killed in this battle while leading a counter-charge near (10 pts)",
        "Prophetstown. Tenskwatawa, the brother of Tecumseh, was defeated at, for ten points, what 1811 battle that coined an enduring nickname for William Henry Harrison?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Tippecanoe"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) AP reporter Robert Geiger first coined this term after witnessing Black Sunday. The SCS was created by Harold Ickes to deal with the aftermath of this event. A shelterbelt of over 200 million (20 pts)",
        "trees was planted by the CCC in the wake of this event. Dorothea Lange’s “Migrant Mother” shows one of millions of displaced (10 pts)",
        "“Okies” fleeing to California for work during this event. For ten points, name this widespread agricultural disaster that plagued the Great Plains during the Great Depression."
      ],
      "answer": "Dust Bowl do not"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The restoration of a modern version of this school of thought was supported by the “Criticize Lin” campaign. The “Two Handles” are emphasized in this school of thought as ways to control the citizenry. (20 pts)",
        "Shang Yang, a philosopher in this school of thought, was responsible for its implementation during the Warring States Period. The most famous proponent of this school of thought ruled the state of (10 pts)",
        "Qin. For ten points, name this ancient Chinese school of political thought focusing on the enforcement of law, notably opposed to Confucianism."
      ],
      "answer": "Legalism"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event was the subject of a painting by Karl Briullov that became the basis for a novel by Edward Bulwer-Lytton. This event was discussed in a letter written from Misenum and addressed to (20 pts)",
        "Tacitus. This event preserved writings like “Gaius Pumidius Diphilus was here,” which had been written as early graffiti. (10 pts)",
        "Pliny the Elder died during this event, which buried Herculaneum in a pyroclastic flow. For ten points, name this event in 79 AD that destroyed the Roman city of Pompeii."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "eruption of Mt. Vesuvius",
        "elaborations",
        "descriptions of “the destruction of Pompeii until “Herculaneum” is read, then"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was banished to Avignon after Charles de Luynes caused the assassination of Concino Concini. This man allied France to Sweden via the Treaty of Barwalde in the (20 pts)",
        "Thirty Years’ War, countering Hapsburg power. This man, who defeated the Duke of Buckingham in the 1627 siege of (10 pts)",
        "La Rochelle, was targeted by Marie de Medici in the Day of the Dupes. For ten points, name this “Red Eminence,” an anti-Huguenot clergyman and chief minister to King Louis XIII [13th] who was succeeded by Cardinal Mazarin."
      ],
      "answer": "Cardinal Richelieu or Armand Jean du Plessis"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this battle, the losing side’s defensive lines were planned by engineer Richard Gridley. The third and final assault on the losing side’s redoubt led to the deaths of both John Pitcairn and Joseph (20 pts)",
        "Warren, and forced Isaac Prescott to withdraw from Charlestown. During this battle, Israel Putnam legendarily told his troops (10 pts)",
        "not to fire until they saw the whites of their enemies’ eyes. William Howe was victorious in, for ten points, what costly 1775 battle outside Boston fought near Breed’s Hill?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Bunker Hill"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event prompted a message from John XXIII [23], in which he begged “all governments not to remain deaf to this cry of humanity.” During this event, negotiations were mediated by U Thant, and Adlai Stevenson famously agitated for an (20 pts)",
        "answer from Valerian Zorin. This event was ended with the removal of (10 pts)",
        "Jupiter weapon systems from Turkey, and it led to the creation of the Moscow-Washington hotline. For ten points, name this 1962 crisis in which the Soviet Union attempted to place weapons on a Caribbean island."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Cuban Missile Crisis",
        "October Crisis",
        "descriptive answers of a diplomatic crisis regarding ballistic missiles placed in Cuba"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The first instance of NATO active combat occurred during this war’s Banja Luka incident, part of Operation Deny Flight. Signs reading “pazi,” meaning “watch out,” were put up in “Sniper (20 pts)",
        "Alley” during this war. Ratko Mladic [m’lah-ditch] was convicted of crimes against humanity for his command during the Srebrenica [sreh-breh-neet-zah] Massacre during this war, which was ended by the (10 pts)",
        "Dayton Agreement in 1995. For ten points, name this war during the breakup of Yugoslavia that included the Siege of Sarajevo."
      ],
      "answer": "Bosnian War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of these systems known as FLOW-MATIC was invented for laypeople by Grace Hopper. Alonzo Church’s lambda calculus serves as the basis for “functional” examples of these constructs, such as Haskell. As depicted in (20 pts)",
        "Hidden Figures, NASA’s Dorothy Vaughn became an expert in one of these constructs known as Fortran. Microsoft’s first product was Altair, an interpreter for one of these constructs named (10 pts)",
        "BASIC. Java, C, and Python are examples of, for ten points, what systems used to write source code, the instructions for a computer program?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "computer programming languages",
        "other additional information"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this event, Helene is killed by a rapist who bites her, though the rapist himself is killed by the apprentice of the wood carver Master Niklaus. This historical event provides the backdrop of Hermann Hesse’s novel (20 pts)",
        "Narcissus and Goldmund. Seven women and three men share a hundred stories with each other while fleeing this event in (10 pts)",
        "Florence in Giovanni Boccaccio’s Decameron. Early treatments of the Danse Macabre motif depict the ravages of, for ten points, what Medieval epidemic?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Black Death",
        "the black plague",
        "the bubonic plague"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1961, this state’s Parchman Farm prison was the site of the detention of more than 300 Freedom Riders. This state’s Sovereignty Commission spied on the civil rights movement here and funded the legal defense of murderer Byron (20 pts)",
        "De La Beckwith. This state’s Freedom Democratic Party attempted to gain official recognition at the 1964 (10 pts)",
        "Democratic National Convention, but was rejected in favor of the all-white delegation. For ten points, name this state where Medgar Evers was murdered in 1963 in its capital of Jackson."
      ],
      "answer": "Mississippi"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) To support this policy, the Duke of Richmond formed the CAPS pressure group, while Richard Cobden and John Bright co-founded a league to protest this policy in Manchester. Charles Pelham (20 pts)",
        "Villiers was the “solitary Robinson Crusoe” calling for repeal of this policy in the House of Commons. The newspaper The Economist was founded to end these laws, which Prime Minister (10 pts)",
        "Robert Peel finally repealed during the Irish Potato Famine. For ten points, name this controversial set of 19th century tariffs and high duties on the import of grains into Great Britain."
      ],
      "answer": "Corn Laws"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man used Omar Khayyam’s quote “So I be written in the Book of Love” to end a seven-hour speech, usually named either “I Believe in the Law of Love” or “A Plea For Mercy,” that was given during the (20 pts)",
        "trials of Ossian Sweet’s family. This man, who represented the killers Leopold and Loeb, questioned (10 pts)",
        "William Jennings Bryan about the factual nature of the Bible during a 1925 show trial in Tennessee. For ten points, name this attorney for the defense in the Scopes Monkey Trial."
      ],
      "answer": "Clarence Darrow"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man oversaw “immorality trials” against Franciscans while spearheading a war against the church in the “Kirchenkampf.” After spending just one day as chancellor, this man poisoned his six (20 pts)",
        "children before committing suicide with his wife. This man, who declared that “if you tell a lie big enough and keep repeating it, people will eventually believe it,” repeatedly assured his country that the (10 pts)",
        "Allies would be defeated with the new V1 rockets. For ten points, name this Nazi minister of propaganda."
      ],
      "answer": "Joseph Goebbels"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One historian claims that the organizers of this event dealt with their opponents by “placing them in shackles, poking them with knives.” Toghon Temur failed to put down this event, which involved a group that was created by Guo Zixing. (20 pts)",
        "Zhu Yuanzhang was one of the main leaders of this event, which was inspired by the teachings of the White (10 pts)",
        "Lotus sect. This 14th century event resulted in the rise of the Hongwu Emperor and the overthrow of the Yuan Dynasty. For ten points, name this rebellion named for the colored headcloth of its rebels."
      ],
      "answer": "Red Turban Rebellion or Hongjin Qiyi"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This battle may have begun when Johnston Pettigrew’s party was send to search for shoes. A clash at Brandy Station took place just before this battle, depriving one side of (20 pts)",
        "JEB Stuart’s cavalry. The 20th Maine regiment was led by Joshua Chamberlain in defending Little (10 pts)",
        "Round Top during this battle, which culminated in an ill-fated attack on Cemetery Ridge by George Pickett’s forces. For ten points, name this 1863 battle in Pennsylvania known as the turning point of the Civil War."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Gettysburg"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The death of a leader in this location led power to shift to the Flensburg government under Karl Donitz. Hans Krebs shot himself in the head as troops closed in on this location, located under the (20 pts)",
        "Chancellery building. This location was the last of its function, preceding the Eagle’s Nest and (10 pts)",
        "Wolf’s Lair. The most famous occupant of this location took cyanide before having his body burnt. For ten points, name this underground command post where Adolf Hitler committed suicide."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Fuhrerbunker",
        "descriptive answers relating to Adolf Hitler’s bunker in Berlin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A ruler with this first name supposedly forged a letter from his mother Emma in order to lure and capture his step-brother Alfred; that ruler had the nickname “Harefoot” and was the son of Canute the Great. A later ruler with this first name used an army of (20 pts)",
        "huscarls to defeat his brother Tostig at the Battle of Stamford Bridge, but was killed by an (10 pts)",
        "arrow to his eye less than a month later. For ten points, give this name shared by the Anglo-Saxon king who lost to William the Conqueror at the Battle of Hastings."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Harold",
        "Harold I",
        "Harold Harefoot",
        "Harold Godwinson after “huscarls” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this war, peace negotiations were held on the USS Lackawanna. In this war, Miguel Grau led the ironclad Huascar to victory at the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Iquique [ee-kee-kay]. This war began after one nation imposed a ten-cent tax on saltpeter, a replacement for guano that was mined from a disputed part of the (10 pts)",
        "Atacama Desert. Peru and Bolivia fought Chile in, for ten points, what 1879 to 1883 war named for a nearby ocean?"
      ],
      "answer": "War of the Pacific"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was criticized in a political cartoon showing him pushing a black man down the throat of a reluctant abolitionist. This man, who once declared “I believe this government was made on the white basis,” argued that (20 pts)",
        "territories could choose to outlaw slavery in the Freeport Doctrine. This author of the (10 pts)",
        "Kansas-Nebraska Act lost the election of 1860 to a political rival he defeated for a Senate seat two years earlier. For ten points, name this politician who famously traveled across Illinois debating Abraham Lincoln."
      ],
      "answer": "Stephen Arnold Douglas"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one work, this man called for a “radical revolution of values” after claiming “[his] conscience leaves [him] no other choice.” Another of this man’s works noted how “no lie can live forever.” This orator of the “How Long, (20 pts)",
        "Not Long” speech claimed that a group has been given a “check which has come back marked insufficient funds” after predicting an “invigorating autumn of (10 pts)",
        "freedom and equality.” In that speech, this man hopes his four children will be “judged not by the color of their skin but by the content of their character.” For ten points, name this civil rights activist who gave the “I Have a Dream” speech."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr.",
        "MLK"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This institution was based on the earlier katorga system, and its growth turned Magadan into an industrial city. This institution was praised in the report Solovki by Maxim Gorky. This system was compared to an (20 pts)",
        "archipelago in an Alexander Solzhenitsyn novel that brought it to the public’s attention. NKVD-led kangaroo (10 pts)",
        "trials led political opponents to be sent to these locations. For ten points, name this system of forced labor camps set up in Siberia under Joseph Stalin."
      ],
      "answer": "gulag system"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man seized the Stone of Destiny after his troops deposed John Balliol at the battle of Dunbar. While leading troops for his father, this man was captured at Lewes but later escaped and defeated the rebellious (20 pts)",
        "Simon de Montfort at the Battle of Evesham. After succeeding (10 pts)",
        "Henry III as king, this man defeated the rebellion of William Wallace to become known as the “hammer of the Scots.” For ten points, name this English king who was nicknamed for his great height."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Edward I",
        "Edward Longshanks"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The central figure of this event was ordered to recite the Seven Penitential Psalms weekly for three years. Robert Bellarmine was a primary antagonist of the target of this event, which occurred several decades after a similar incident resulted in the (20 pts)",
        "execution of Giordano Bruno. Publications like The Starry Messenger were condemned as part of this event, whose target was sentenced to (10 pts)",
        "house arrest in 1633. For ten points, name this event which forced an Italian to recant his heliocentric claims."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "trial of Galileo Galilei",
        "descriptive equivalents"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) As a twelve-year-old, this man once personally called Bill Hewlett of Hewlett-Packard for parts to build a frequency counter. Tim Berners-Lee ran the first browser on the World Wide Web using a device created by this man’s company (20 pts)",
        "NeXT Inc. This man became a member of Disney’s board of directors following the purchase of (10 pts)",
        "Pixar, of which he was CEO. This man is most famous for founding a company that sold “Nano” and “Shuffle” versions of its iPod. For ten points, name this late co-founder and CEO of Apple."
      ],
      "answer": "Steve Jobs"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This battle led to the sacking of Ian Hamilton after numerous unsuccessful attempts to capture Scimitar Hill during the August Offensive. The losing side attempted to secure footholds at (20 pts)",
        "Cape Helles and ANZAC Cove during this battle. Winston Churchill (10 pts)",
        "resigned as First Lord of the Admiralty as a result of this battle, where Allied troops were repulsed by Mustafa Kemal. For ten points, name this 1915 campaign that sought to capture a namesake strait from the Ottoman Empire."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Gallipoli",
        "Dardanelles Campaign"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) At this battle, Charles Wikoff and three other commanders were injured or killed in under an hour, leading Ezra Ewers to assume command. The winning side at this battle came under fire from Mausers at a location called (20 pts)",
        "“Bloody Ford.” Troops from El Caney provided support for this side’s victors. Though the Buffalo Soldiers were prominent at this battle, it is more often associated with a (10 pts)",
        "cavalry unit that went on to fight at the Siege of Santiago. For ten points, name this 1898 battle in Cuba where Teddy Roosevelt fought with the Rough Riders."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of San Juan Hill",
        "Battle of San Juan Heights"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A 17th century migration led to the rise of this industry in the town of Spitalfields. Garreurs and battandiers were types of workers in this industry that led a revolt put down by Jean-de-Dieu Soult. The (20 pts)",
        "Canut revolts occurred in this industry which was controlled by a class of financiers called fabricants. Louis XVI promoted this industry in the city of (10 pts)",
        "Lyon. James I promoted the trade of this good by planting 100,000 mulberry plants. For ten points, name this textile good that is produced by a namesake worm."
      ],
      "answer": "silk"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Followers of this denomination travel on the Arba’een pilgrimage, one of the largest in the world. That event is part of this denomination’s remembrance of the death of Husayn ibn Ali at the Battle of Karbala, the (20 pts)",
        "Mourning of Muharram, which includes the day of Ashura. This denomination, which includes Sevener and Twelver schools, believes that (10 pts)",
        "Muhammad appointed his son-in-law Ali as successor. For ten points, name this denomination dominant in Azerbaijan and Iran, the second-biggest denomination of Islam behind Sunni Islam."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Shia Islam",
        "Shi’ites"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) To help ease the burden caused by taxes on the financing of these objects, Periandros introduced a system called the symmories. Polycrates provided forty of these objects in the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Pelusium. During the First Punic War, these were among the smaller vessels outfitted with a hook-like boarding tool called a corvus. One of these vessels provided news of defeat to the (10 pts)",
        "Athenians after the Battle of Aegospotami. For ten points, name these ancient ships named for the fact that they had three rows of oars."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "triremes",
        "triremis"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The longest single story in the Quran re-tells the life of this prophet. The Biblical book named for this prophet is read as haftarah on the afternoon of Yom Kippur. This man, who prophecies to a group of people who “could not tell their right hand from their left,” gets (20 pts)",
        "belligerent after a fast-growing gourd-vine he was using for shade gets eaten by a worm. This prophet tried to (10 pts)",
        "sail to Tarshish to avoid prophesying doom to Nineveh as he was commanded. For ten points, name this Biblical prophet who is swallowed by a huge fish."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Jonah or Jonas",
        "or Yunus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A signatory of the Declaration of Independence from this state named John Witherspoon helped shift the emphasis of one of its universities away from clerical training. A governor of this colony who believed the Stamp Act was justified was an (20 pts)",
        "illegitimate son of Benjamin Franklin named William. Known as the Crossroads of the Revolution, this state is home to a (10 pts)",
        "university attended by James Madison and Aaron Burr; that university shares its name with a nearby 1777 battle. For ten points, name this home state of Princeton University."
      ],
      "answer": "New Jersey"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man signed a treaty with Chief Bowl to guarantee Cherokee land rights, though his friendship with the natives led to a feud with senator William Stanberry, who this man attacked with a (20 pts)",
        "cane. This man was replaced from his highest post by Mirabeau Lamar after refusing to join the Confederacy. As a general, this man took only (10 pts)",
        "18 minutes to win the Battle of San Jacinto against Santa Anna. For ten points, name this fighter for Texan independence and namesake of the most populous city in Texas."
      ],
      "answer": "Sam Houston"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Xanthippus, the father of Pericles, rivaled this man and was ostracized, but was later allowed to return and replaced this man as commander at the Battle of Mycale. This man used the silver from the (20 pts)",
        "Laurium mines to build 100 triremes, over the objections of his rival, Aristides. This (10 pts)",
        "naval commander was exiled to Argos, and earlier won the Battle of Artemisium. For ten points, name this Athenian who led Greek forces to victory at Salamis."
      ],
      "answer": "Themistocles"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader attempted to conquer Viborg from Sweden, but was stopped by the forces of Knut Posse. After the death of his first wife Maria of Tver, this man was encouraged by the Pope to marry the ex-Byzantine princess (20 pts)",
        "Zoe Palaiologos. This man famously forced Akhmat to retreat during the Great Stand on the Ugra River, which ended Tatar rule in his lands. Later in his rule, he carried out a mass (10 pts)",
        "renovation of the walls of the Kremlin. For ten points, name this grand prince of Moscow, the first to gather the lands of Rus under one crown."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Ivan III Vasilyevich",
        "Ivan the Great"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A member of this family exiled the Strozzi and launched a war against Lucca. Opponents of this family included Francesco Salviati, who orchestrated a plot to kill some of its members during high Mass in the (20 pts)",
        "Pazzi conspiracy. The Albizzi attempted to curb the influence of this family by expelling one of their leading members, but that man, (10 pts)",
        "Cosimo, returned the next year. Pope Leo X was a member of this family, as was Lorenzo the Magnificent. Michelangelo was under the patronage of, for ten points, what family that ruled medieval Florence?"
      ],
      "answer": "Medici family"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An order to destroy this ship may have been rescinded when Thomas Hardy’s wife allegedly broke into tears upon hearing the news. In its early career, this ship served as the flagship for Augustus Keppel at the Ushants. This ship was painted (20 pts)",
        "black and yellow so it could be more easily identified in a battle where it led a fleet into splitting the lines of Pierre Villeneuve. The (10 pts)",
        "expectation that “every man do their duty” was broadcast from this ship, whose commander was killed in action against a Franco-Spanish fleet. For ten points, name this flagship for Horatio Nelson at Trafalgar."
      ],
      "answer": "HMS Victory"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Carole Pateman argued that this concept leads to the patriarchal domination of women. A work titled for this concept claims that countries in hot climates are more likely to be monarchies and notes that the power of the state is split between the (20 pts)",
        "government and the people, who represent the general will. The line “Man is (10 pts)",
        "born free; and everywhere he is in chains” opens a work titled for, for ten points, what political relationship in which people agree to be ruled by the state, discussed in a namesake book by Jean-Jacques Rousseau?"
      ],
      "answer": "social contract"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this century, Ruy L´opez de Villalobos came up with the name for the Philippines. Juan de Sepu´lveda engaged in a debate at Valladolid over the definition of natural slavery with Bartolome de las Casas during this century. The (20 pts)",
        "Revolt of the Comuneros occurred in this century, during which Joanna the Mad’s son ruled. Holy Roman Emperor Charles (10 pts)",
        "V supported the Council of Trent during this century and funded the expedition of Ferdinand Magellan. For ten points, name this century that began eight years after the first voyage of Christopher Columbus."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "1500s",
        "16th century"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Three years after his death, this man’s corpse was dug up, hanged alongside Henry Ireton and John Bradshaw, and beheaded, with his head mounted on a stake above Westminster Hall. This man, whose forces (20 pts)",
        "massacred the citizens of Drogheda when they refused to surrender, worked with Thomas Fairfax to win the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Naseby. This man dissolved the Rump Parliament after leading the New Model Army to victory against Charles I. For ten points, name this Parliamentarian commander who became Lord Protector of England."
      ],
      "answer": "Oliver Cromwell"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) To deal with members of this group after the 1838 Battle of Crooked River, Lilburn Boggs put out Missouri Executive Order 44, an “Extermination Order.” A leader of this group who was killed in Carthage, Illinois allegedly met with (20 pts)",
        "Moroni, an angel who handed down golden plates that became this religion’s central text. Members of this religion briefly created the state of (10 pts)",
        "Deseret, which was governed by Brigham Young. Joseph Smith founded, for ten points, what Christian denomination that is the majority religion of Utah?"
      ],
      "answer": "Mormons"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The losing side in this battle allegedly began to throw oranges and lemons after running out of usable weapons. In this battle, Marcantonio Colonna withstood an attack from Uluc Ali’s fleet in the Gulf of Patras in this battle, which was preceded by a siege of (20 pts)",
        "Famagusta. Author Miguel de Cervantes lost an arm fighting in this battle, the last major battle of (10 pts)",
        "rowing ships. The Real [ray-AHL] served as the flagship of Don Juan of Austria, the winning commander of, for ten points, what 1571 battle, a massive naval defeat for the Ottoman Empire?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Lepanto"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event was triggered by an accident involving barrels of benzol. Vince Coleman sent a telegram reading “Hold up the train. [...] Guess this will be my last message. Good-bye boys.”, which saved hundreds of passengers from riding directly into this event. A (20 pts)",
        "half-ton piece of metal that was thrown over 2 miles away is now a monument to this event; that metal was part of the anchor of the SS (10 pts)",
        "Mont Blanc, whose cargo caught fire. For ten points, name this December 6, 1917 tragedy in which over 2,000 people were killed in Nova Scotia in the largest pre-nuclear, man-made explosion in history."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Halifax explosion",
        "descriptions of the SS Mont Blanc explosion before mentioned",
        "“explosion” not needed after mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Ma Rulong led the Hui people during a rebellion against this dynasty before defecting to this dynasty’s side. The lives of Shang Zhixin’s thirty-two brothers were spared in the aftermath of Wu Sangui’s uprising against this dynasty; that incident, the Revolt of the (20 pts)",
        "Three Feudatories, was won by this dynasty’s Green Standard Army, which mobilized under the command of the Kangxi Emperor. This dynasty defeated (10 pts)",
        "Li Zicheng’s forces at the Battle of Shanhai Pass to end the short-lived Shun dynasty. For ten points, name this Chinese dynasty founded by descendants of the Jurchen people, called Manchus."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Qing dynasty",
        "Manchus before read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This policy was supported by a Payment Law that suspended government subsidies for non-adherents. A disgruntled Edward Kullman was angered into a failed assassination attempt by this policy, which spurred the formation of Ludwig Windthorst’s (20 pts)",
        "Center Party. This policy was strengthened with the passing of Adalbert (10 pts)",
        "Falk’s May Laws, and it led to a ban on Jesuits. For ten points, name this general policy against the Catholic Church that was put forth by Otto von Bismarck."
      ],
      "answer": "Kulturkampf"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This battle proceeded when Forrest Sherman overruled James Doyle on the implementation of Plan 100B. A feint by the HMS Whitesand Bay helped maintain the element of surprise for this battle, which began when one side entered the Flying Fish Channel to strike at (20 pts)",
        "Green, Red, and Blue beaches. Kimpo Airfield was taken as a result of this battle. This battle, codenamed Operation (10 pts)",
        "Chromite, broke the siege of the Pusan Perimeter and led to the recapture of Seoul. Douglas MacArthur masterminded, for ten points, what 1950 amphibious landing that turned the Korean War?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Inchon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) With Bill Nichols, this man sponsored a bill to reorganize the Department of Defense. This man’s policies were targeted by the “Ice Cream” Ad and another ad that ended “We must (20 pts)",
        "love each other, or we must die.” In one campaign, this man’s slogan “In your heart, you know he’s right” was mocked by his opponent’s slogan “In your gut, you know he’s nuts.” The book Conscience of a (10 pts)",
        "Conservative was written by, for ten points, what five-time senator from Arizona who lost in a landslide election to Lyndon Johnson in 1964?"
      ],
      "answer": "Barry Goldwater"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This family’s first ruler was pressured to retire to the Stoudion monastery on the advice of Michael Psellos. A history of this family was written by Anna and describes the suspicion this family held towards (20 pts)",
        "Bohemond of Taranto. This family’s most famous ruler sent his ambassadors to the Council of Piacenza after a defeat at (10 pts)",
        "Manzikert. In response to Seljuk expansion, Pope Urban II called for knights to come aid this family. For ten points, name this Byzantine ruling family that, during the First Crusade, was led by Alexius I."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Komnenos dynasty",
        "Komnenids",
        "Komnenoi"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A popular piece of propaganda during this scandal was the fabricated story of a boy being stabbed with a bayonet while trying to save his bunny. Pelham Glassford resigned as police superintendent in the wake of this event. Future generals (20 pts)",
        "Patton, MacArthur, and Eisenhower were among the forces called to action in this event, which took place on the Anacostia Flats. (10 pts)",
        "Herbert Hoover was heavily criticized for his response to, for ten points, what “expeditionary force” of twenty thousand men who, in 1932, demanded early payment of their World War I service certificates?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Bonus Army",
        "Bonus Expeditionary Force"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The first holder of this post lasted only thirteen days in power after William Fox defeated Henry Sewell in election. Holders of this post refused to accept the autonomy offered in the 1931 Statute of Westminster until George (20 pts)",
        "Forbes took power. Finland’s Sanna Marin beat a record set by the current holder of this post as the world’s youngest female leader. This office was held for thirteen years by Richard (10 pts)",
        "Seddon, who used his tenure to annex the Cook Islands and buy land from the native Maori. Jacinda Ardern currently holds, for ten points, what post that heads a government in Wellington?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Prime Minister of New Zealand",
        "premier of New Zealand"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Elizabeth Drinker unsuccessfully appealed to this woman in an attempt to free a group of Quaker soldiers who failed to give a loyalty oath. This woman’s marriage to Daniel Parke Custis ended with his death, leaving her with over 300 (20 pts)",
        "slaves and a massive estate at age 25. In 1777, this woman attended a production of the play Cato put on by soldiers at (10 pts)",
        "Valley Forge during a visit to meet her more famous second husband. For ten points, name this matriarch of Mount Vernon, the wife of George Washington."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Martha Washington",
        "Martha Dandridge",
        "Martha Custis before “Custis” is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After the Farmington disaster of 1968 involving this resource, a Federal Health and Safety Act was passed to protect people working in the business associated with this resource. A 1920 shootout between laborers in this industry and members of the Baldwin-Felts Detective Agency took place in (20 pts)",
        "Matewan, West Virginia. Workers who help to extract this resource can suffer from excessive powder inhalation, or (10 pts)",
        "“black lung.” For ten points, name this sedimentary fossil fuel, extracted from underground “seams.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Coal"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Hurley Medical Center led two studies on this event, including one by Mona Hanna-Attisha. LeeAnne Walters won the Goldman Prize for her advocacy during this event. Mayor Dayne Walling lost to Karen Weaver following this event, which occurred after a contract with the (20 pts)",
        "Karegnondi Water Authority. Rick Snyder declared a state of emergency during this event in Genesee County. This event involved the release of corrosive (10 pts)",
        "lead from pipes sourced from the Detroit River. For ten points, name this public health crisis in Michigan."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Flint Water Crisis",
        "descriptive answers of the water crisis in Flint"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During the Middle Ages, this man was the only commander on record using \"feigned retreat,” such as at the Battle of Amblève. Ragenfrid and Chilperic II were defeated by this man at Vinchy. Dagobert III's son, Theuderic IV, had his reign controlled by this man who was himself the son of (20 pts)",
        "Pepin of Herstal. This man was jailed by Plectrude in Cologne, the site of his only defeat. This man defeated Abdul Rahman Al-Ghafiqi and the Umayyads at (10 pts)",
        "Tours. For ten points, name this Frankish ruler, known as \"the Hammer.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Charles Martel"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) William Glenn and William Sewell built one of these devices using erector pieces. Vladimir Demikhov made the first of these devices, one of which Henry Optik received from General Motors Research. In Houston, Michael DeBakey worked with one of these devices called an LVAD. Willem Johan Kolff and Robert (20 pts)",
        "Jarvik worked on the development of these devices, one of which was implanted in dentist Barney Clark who lived 112 (10 pts)",
        "days afterwards. SynCardia is an example of, for ten points, what type of device that replaces a blood pumping organ?"
      ],
      "answer": "Artificial heart"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This sect was defended in the Old Order Movement, and their Abecedarian sect rejected all learning. In the 1920s, this sect included the Bruderhof. Nicholas Storch, Thomas Dreschel, and Markus Stubner formed a trio that were the predecessors of this (20 pts)",
        "religious group. This group, which had the Schleitheim Confession and the Ausbund, was preceded by the Zwickau Prophets. Members of this group included Melchior Hoffan, Jacob Hutter, and (10 pts)",
        "Menno Simons, who names the Mennonites. For ten points, name this Protestant group that allowed for adult re-baptism."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Anabaptists",
        "Anabaptism, anti"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man became an army lieutenant in 1878, at the age of 14, and was made Inspector General of the Armed Forces in 1913. In 1889, this man’s cousin Rudolf took his own life in a suicide pact with his mistress, leaving this man (20 pts)",
        "second in line for the throne. On the condition that his descendants would be excluded from the line of succession, this man was permitted to marry Countess (10 pts)",
        "Sophie Chotek in 1899. For ten points, name this Archduke whose assassination at the hands of Gavrilo Princip precipitated the First World War."
      ],
      "answer": "Archduke Franz Ferdinand of Austria"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Corruption in this federal agency, abetted by the first female administrator of this agency, Anne Gorsuch, was uncovered in the early-1980’s. Members of this agency were taken hostage by protestors led by Lois Gibbs during the Love (20 pts)",
        "Canal Crisis. This agency was originally formed in response to fiascos like the waste-fueled fires on the Cuyahoga River. The publication of Rachel Carson’s (10 pts)",
        "Silent Spring was key to the movement that led to the Nixon administration’s creation of, for ten points, what federal agency intended to fight pollution?"
      ],
      "answer": "Environmental Protection Agency or EPA"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this year, Norfolk, Virginia was burned and looted on New Year’s Day. Chatterton Hill was taken in this year at the Battle of White Plains. In this year, Richard Caswell led the Patriots in the Battle of Moore's Bridge, and John Sullivan helped defeat the forces of Johann (20 pts)",
        "Rall at a battle in this year. At McConkey's Ferry in this year, Henry Knox and George Washington (10 pts)",
        "crossed the Delaware River. The Battle of Trenton occurred in, for ten points, what year, which featured the ringing of the Liberty Bell and signing of the Declaration of Independence."
      ],
      "answer": "1776"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1970, this man distributed fake campaign flyers at a rock concert to disrupt the election of Alan Dixon. This man was opposed by Robert Edgeworth and Terry Dolan to head the College Republicans. This man used “push (20 pts)",
        "polling” to insinuate that a candidate's staff was \"dominated by lesbians\" to help his client beat Ann Richards. This man helped elect men like John Ashcroft, Bill Clements, and John (10 pts)",
        "Cornyn. Nicknamed the \"Architect,” for ten points, name this Chief Strategist and Chief of Staff for George W. Bush."
      ],
      "answer": "Karl Rove"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This character’s origins can be traced as far back as Molière’s Don Juan, or The Stone Guest. Jean-Honoré Fragonard depicted this character as a boy forcing a taciturn smile. In Antoine Watteau’s painting of this character, dressed in his traditional (20 pts)",
        "baggy white clothes, he was given the name “Gilles.” This character loses his love interest Columbine to Harlequin, resulting in his perpetual (10 pts)",
        "disconsolate demeanor. For ten points, name this staple character of commedia dell'arte, the embodiment of the sad clown."
      ],
      "answer": "Pierrot ]"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Details of this event were first revealed in an anonymous letter sent to William Parker, 4th Baron Monteagle. Some of the men involved in planning this event battled the Sheriff of Worcester [[WOO-ster]] at Holbeche [[\"HOLE\"-beech]] House, where this event’s leader, (20 pts)",
        "Robert Catesby [[KATES-bee]], was killed. Eight of the conspirators involved in this event were convicted at a subsequent trial, including (10 pts)",
        "Guy Fawkes. For ten points, name this failed plan to destroy the House of Lords and assassinate King James I."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Gunpowder Plot or Gunpowder Treason Plot",
        "Jesuit Treason"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Under this prime minister, a scandal over the merger of Westland Helicopters led to the resignation of Defense Secretary Michael Heseltine. “Flying (20 pts)",
        "pickets” were used by National Union of Mineworkers during a strike under this prime minister. This leader’s victory in the Falklands War allowed a landslide Conservative victory in the 1983 (10 pts)",
        "general election. For ten points, name this “Iron Lady,” the prime minister of the United Kingdom during the 1980s."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Margaret Thatcher or Margaret Hilda Thatcher",
        "Baroness Thatcher"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This party accepted opponent William Pitt Kellogg's election as governor of Louisiana in exchange for house seats in the Wheeler Compromise. This party's historical factions included the white supremacist (20 pts)",
        "Redeemers, the pro-big business Bourbons, and the Populists of William Jennings Bryan. This party controlled the \"Solid South,\" though it lost control of Southern states during the Reagan era. Represented by a (10 pts)",
        "donkey, for ten points, what U.S. political party opposes the Republicans?"
      ],
      "answer": "Democratic Party or Democrats"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This monument’s astylar design was developed by the Neoclassical sculptor Jean Chalgrin [[SHAHL-grin]]. The base of this monument contains four sculptural groups, including one by Antoine (*) Etex said to commemorate the Peace of 1815 and one by François [[frahn-SWAH]] Rude called Departure of the Volunteers of 1792. The Tomb of the Unknown Soldier beneath this monument was commissioned after the Battle of (*) Austerlitz. For ten points, name this monument found at the western end of the Champs-Élysées [[SHAHMPS eh-lee-SAY]] in Paris."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Arc de Triomphe de l'Étoile",
        "Triumphal Arch of the Star"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Attempts to suppress news of this document were countered by a group of secret messengers called the 4Ls. This document specifically exempted the cities of Norfolk and Portsmouth and it contained a window of three months during which targeted (20 pts)",
        "states could avoid its provisions. This document was held in reserve to avoid appearing \"the last shriek of retreat\" and was issued after the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Antietam. For ten points, name this 1863 document released by Abraham Lincoln, which freed slaves in secessionist states."
      ],
      "answer": "Emancipation Proclamation or Proclamation 95"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The so-called \"Land Pirate,\" John Murrell, faced allegations of starting one of these events along the Mississippi River in a namesake \"Excitement.\" The testimony of George Wilson and Joe LaRoche quashed another of these events planned by a man known as (20 pts)",
        "Telemaque [[teh-leh-MAHK]] in Charleston. One of these events in Southampton, Virginia was suppressed at Belmont (10 pts)",
        "Plantation. For ten points, name these uprisings, one of which was led by Nat Turner."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Slave Rebellion",
        "equivalents like Slave Uprising",
        "specific answers like \"Denmark Vesey's Revolt\"",
        "Nat Turner's Revolt",
        "\"Enslaved Person\" in place of \"Slave\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An Aristophanes [[ah-reh-STOH-fah-nees]] play titled for this occupation included a competition of who can be more shameless between a sausage seller and an analogue of the politician Creon. Arcite [[ahr-SEE-teh]] and Palamon are (20 pts)",
        "two soldiers imprisoned in a tower by Theseus and fall in love with his sister-in-law Emelye [[\"Emily\"]] in a \"Tale\" (10 pts)",
        "named for this profession. In one story, Gawain battles a \"Green\" one of these people. For ten points, name this medieval chivalric class of warriors."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Knights",
        "The Knights",
        "Knight's Tale",
        "Hippeis"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A bank connected to this man run by Roberto Calvi faced controversy after it funneled money to both sides of the Nicaraguan Civil War. This figure narrowly escaped the Nazi Black Sunday roundup of youth after the Warsaw (20 pts)",
        "Ghetto uprising, hiding in his uncle’s basement in Krakow. Grey Wolves member Mehmet Ali Agca [[AHD-juh]] fired and injured this (10 pts)",
        "holy figure in St. Peter’s Square. For ten points, name this Polish Pope who was succeeded by Benedict XVI [[the sixteenth]]."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Pope John Paul II or Ioannes Paulus II",
        "Karol Józef Wojtyła"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While happening upon this event, Beat poet Allen Ginsberg allegedly said “it’s about time that we did something to assert ourselves.” Sylvia Riviera has been mythologized as the person that “threw the first brick at [this event].” This event, which occurred a week after Judy (20 pts)",
        "Garland’s death, broke out after lesbian Stormé DeLarverie [[stor-MAY deh-LAR-veh-ree]] was arrested and assaulted by (10 pts)",
        "New York police. For ten points, name this 1969 LGBTQ “riot” that began at a Greenwich Village gay bar."
      ],
      "answer": "Stonewall Inn Riot"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Days prior to an event at this site, Mikhail Gorbachev met with a world leader for a summit at a nearby locale at the Great Hall of the People. A gathering in this location was precipitated by the death of the reformist Hu (20 pts)",
        "Yaobang [[HOO-YAO- BAHNG]]. Constructed during the Ming Dynasty in 1415, perhaps the most iconic photo taken at this location was of an unidentified man (10 pts)",
        "blocking tanks on a road. For ten points, name this Chinese location that was the site of mass protests and a massacre in 1989."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Tiananmen Square",
        "Tiananmen Square protests",
        "Tiananmen Square massacre"
      ]
    }
  ]
}